<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><Search><pages Count="58"><page Index="1"><![CDATA[INDIRA GANDHI INSTITUTE OF

                      DEVELOPMENT RESEARCH









   A P R I L   2 0 2 1   E D I T I O N                                       V O L U M E   0 1   |   I S S U E   0 1

              E C O N P ₹ I S M









  COVID-19: IMPACT & LESSONS LEARNT

































































                            I G I D R   S T U D E N T   N E W S L E T T E R]]></page><page Index="2"><![CDATA[C O N T R I B U T O R S






                                             I G I D R   N E W S L E T T E R



                                       F A C U L T Y   A D V I S O R S

                                                  Bharti Nandwani

                                           Gopakumar Achuthankutty



                                                   E D I T O R S


                                        Chitralekha Sudhakar Gaikwad
                                                  Gaorima Nahata

                                                        Khushi
                                                 Medha Chatterjee

                                                     Rimi Gupta
                                                   Shrey Saurabh

                                                   Swarupjit Palit


                                             D E S I G N   T E A M


                                                    Shirsha Saha

                                                        Ujjawal


                                               V O L U N T E E R S


                                                 Alumni Committee

                                                    Charu Nagpal

                                                Romit Abhichandani


                                    W E B S I T E   &   F L I P B O O K


                                             Promit Kanti Chaudhuri]]></page><page Index="3"><![CDATA[TABLE OF CONTENTS













              E  D  I  T  O  R  I  A  L     B  O  A  R  D


              M  E  S  S  A  G  E     C  O  R  N  E  R

              • Director's Note
              • Faculty Advisors' Note



              A  R  T  I  C  L  E  S     F  R  O  M     E  X  P  E  R  T  S
                 One Year of Covid-19 and the Indian Economy by Dr. S. Mahendra Dev
                 Get by with a little help from friends (and shopkeepers): Household borrowing in response to
                 Covid-19 by Dr. Ajay Shah and Dr. Renuka Sane
                 Covid-19: The Invisible Vicious Foe by Dr. Namrata Gulati and Chandni Nanda




              I  N  T  E  R  V  I  E  W
                 Dr. Srijit Mishra




              A  R  T  I  C  L  E  S     F  R  O  M     S  T  U  D  E  N  T  S
                 Shibanjan Dutta
                 Sagar Kumar




              C  A  M  P  U  S     A  C  T  I  V  I  T  I  E  S
                 Covid-19: Impact and Lessons Learnt by Jai Mohan Pandit, Registrar
                 Library Services during Covid-19 by Library Team
                 Campus Recruitment in a Pandemic-Struck Economy by Lukshya Verma
                 Alumni Committee
                 Kaawish




              F  U  N     C  O  R  N  E  R
                 Crossword
                 Jumbled Words




              N  O  S  T  A  L  G  I  A]]></page><page Index="4"><![CDATA[DIRECTOR                                                       DIRECTOR' S NOTE








                    IGIDR
















                                                       IGIDR, conceptualized as a think tank in

                                                       development policy by the then Reserve
                                                       Bank  of  India  (RBI)  governor  Dr.

                                                       Manmohan  Singh,  is  an  autonomous

                                                       research  body  founded  in  1987  by  the

                                                       RBI to commemorate its golden jubilee.

                                                       Its mission is to promote the study and
                                                       dissemination             of     knowledge,           and
      S. M AHEN D R A D EV
                                                       conduct         research         from        a     broad

       I am happy that IGIDR students                  interdisciplinary              perspective,             on

           are bringing out the first                  development             with        its      economic,

      quarterly issue of the newsletter.               technological,  social,  political,  and
       I thank the editorial committee                 ecological  aspects,  to  gain  insights  into

       including faculty members and                   the  process  of  development  and
       students for this initiative. This              alternative  policy  options,  with  special

       gives an opportunity for IGIDR
                                                       emphasis on social, legal, organizational
        to showcase its academic and
                                                       and institutional aspects.
        non-academic activities of the
          institute. It can also create

           synergy between IGIDR
         activities and those of other

        academicians, policy makers,
          regulatory bodies, and the

      corporate sector. Thanks are also
       due to the IQAC sub-committee

        for their recommendations on

                the newsletter.
                                                                                                                  1]]></page><page Index="5"><![CDATA[Here,  I  would  like  to  share  the  message  given  at  successive  directors  as  well  as  the  continuous
       the time of the Silver Jubilee year of the institute    encouragement and  support  of  the  Reserve  Bank
       in  2012/13  by  Dr.  Manmohan  Singh  who  was  the    of  India  and  its  successive  Governing  Board
       then Prime Minister. The message is the following.      Members.


       “I  extend  my  greetings  to  the  faculty,  staff  and  The  research  agenda  of  IGIDR  is  guided  by
       students  of  the  Indira  Gandhi  Institute  of        contemporary  policy  concerns,  individual  faculty
       Development  Research  (IGIDR),  as  the  institute     members’     research   interests,   and   through
       celebrates its silver Jubilee this year.                sponsored  projects.  Theoretical  as  well  as
                                                               empirical  research  undertaken  over  the  years
       It  is  with  great  fondness  that  I  look  back  at  the  covers a wide range of topics and themes such as
       time when the idea of IGIDR was conceived during        macroeconomics,  banking  and  finance,  household
       my  tenure  as  Governor,  Reserve  Bank  of  India.    finance  and  financial  sector  regulation,  poverty,
       Though it was initially conceived as an Economics       inequality and human development, food security
       think tank for the country, IGIDR was inaugurated       and  agriculture,  industrial  organisation  and
       as  an  advanced  research  institute  in  1987  by  the  corporate  governance,  international  finance  and
       then Prime Minister Shri Rajiv Gandhi.                  trade,  development  economics,  public  economics,
                                                               institutional  and  law  and  economics,  energy  and
       I am happy that IGIDR has emerged as a centre of        environment     policy,   urban   economics     and
       excellence  for  higher  learning  in  economics,       migration,  and  city  planning.  These  areas  of
       focusing  on  academic  training  and  research  from   research  focus  reflect  the  diverse  expertise  and
       an interdisciplinary and international perspective.     interests  of  its  faculty,  both  past  and  current.
       It has gained status as a deemed university in 1995     IGIDR’s  research  would  continue  to  stay  focused
       and has been accredited with the highest ranking        on various developmental problems and issues of
       for its teaching and research programmes.               policy relevance as they evolve from time to time.
                                                               At the same time, the Institute recognizes the need
       In  these  challenging  times,  our  country  needs     to  expand  its  research  profile  in  some  of  the
       quality  academic  inputs  into  the  policy  making    emerging areas to maintain its stature as a premier
       exercise. It is this challenge that IGIDR should take   institution  for  research  in  economics  and  public
       up as it prepares for the years ahead.                  policy.

       I congratulate all those who have been associated       The Institute will seek to enhance faculty strength
       with  IGIDR’s  growth  and  development.  I  wish       – both regular and visiting faculty – in a few of the
       them and IGIDR all the best for the future."            emerging  research  areas.  A  decentralized  system
                                                               for  faculty  and  students  has  provided  a  free
       Over  the  years,  IGIDR  has  established  itself  as  a  intellectual  space  for  research  ideas,  within  the
       premier  research  cum-teaching  institute  and  its    broad theme of Development.
       current eminence derives in a large measure from
       the efforts of its faculty, students and staff,         Right from the beginning IGIDR has had a




                                                                                                                  2]]></page><page Index="6"><![CDATA[tremendous  impact  on  policy  debates  of  national    (albeit  carrying  out  interdisciplinary  research)
       and  international  importance.  Going  forward,         Deemed  to  be  Univerisity  to  a  full-fledged  multi-
       IGIDR  will  continue  to  stress  on  policy  relevant  disciplinary   university   /   higher   education
       research by its faculty and students.                    institution  (HEI).  This  requires  fundamental
                                                                decisions to be taken by the institute on all aspects,
       Right  from  the  beginning  IGIDR  has  had  a          including IGIDR’s mission and vision.
       tremendous  impact  on  policy  debates  of  national
       and  international  importance.  Going  forward,         It is important to have a broader and at the same
       IGIDR  will  continue  to  stress  on  policy  relevant  time  well  defined  area  where  the  institute  should
       research by its faculty and students. The Institute      focus  while  planning  to  reorient  and  expand.  The
       will continue to publish the widely regarded India       broad area of public policy is one such overarching
       Development  Report.  The  Institute  will  also         theme,  where  the  institute  can  leverage  on  its
       encourage  and  provide  all  possible  support  to  its  current  strength.  Apart  from  economics,  a  good
       faculty  for  participation  in  official  policy  making  public  policy  HEI/university  should  have  multiple
       Committees  of  various  Ministries.  Besides,  the      departments  such  as,  politics,  international
       Institute  will  continue  to  play  a  leading  role  in  relations,   demography,     geography,      law,
       policy debates by organising thematic conferences        management, statistics, and environmental studies
       and workshops on its own and/or at the request of        etc.  Thus,  expansion  along  these  lines  will  ensure
       various  Government  Ministries  /  policy  making       that   we    can   become     a   multidisciplinary
       bodies.  Strengthening  teaching  and  expanding         HEI/university as envisaged in NEP but with great
       outreach activities are part of the vision.              synergy among the various departments.

       One of the immediate challenges of the institute is      In   keeping    with   NEP-2020,    the   teaching
       to align with the guidelines of the New Education        programme  has  to  be  diversified  broadly  on  two
       Policy-2020   (NEP-2020)    announced     by   the       lines:  (a)  The  first  one  is  to  start  differentiated
       government.                                              degree programmes at the Masters level that have a
                                                                strong  core  in  Economics  but  specialisation  in
       It lays down the government’s vision, approach and       specific  application  fields.  Examples  include  M.Sc.
       the framework for the entire education sector from       in  Financial  Economics  and  M.Sc.  in  Energy  and
       primary  education  to  higher  education.  The  NEP-    Environment Economics; (b) Second one is to start
       2020  has  far  reaching  implications  for  IGIDR  in   a  4-year  B.Sc.  in  Economics  programme.  In  this
       terms  of  its  nature,  scope,  size,  and  academic    regard,  the  Institute  could  consider  some  of  the
       programmes. Fundamentally, the NEP-2020 would            ideas described in the NEP-2020 for 3-year and 4-
       require IGIDR to transform from a single-discipline      year undergraduate programmes.






                                                                                                                  3]]></page><page Index="7"><![CDATA[The intellectual ambience of

                                                                        openness to ideas and

                                                                   plurality of perspectives have

                                                                          to be continued and

                                                                               strengthened.






















       As  a  think-tank  in  public  policy,  IGIDR’s  vision  is  to  become  the  premier  nodal  centre  for  development
       research  in  India  over  the  next  10  years  for  promoting  cooperative  endeavours  with  other  Indian  and
       International scholars and institutions; to organize courses, capacity building programs, conferences, and
       workshops  on  subjects  of  theoretical  or  practical  relevance  for  development  and  policy  formulation;  to

       publish  journals,  reports,  pamphlets,  books,  research  papers  in  furtherance  of  these  objectives;  and  to
       provide  consultancy  to  national  and  international  institutions  on  issues  linked  to  these  objectives.  The
       vision of IGIDR in the next decade is to further develop it as an Institute of high international standing and
       join the league of world class centres of excellence in theoretically informed applied research and teaching
       in development studies. It can be done by strengthening the present areas of research and diversifying its
       research  and  teaching  to  new  areas  to  address  the  development  challenges  in  tune  with  the  changes  in

       development paradigms, economy and society. The intellectual ambience of openness to ideas and plurality
       of perspectives have to be continued and strengthened.

                                                                                               S. MAHENDRA DEV
                                                                                                           Director

















                                                                                                                 4]]></page><page Index="8"><![CDATA[FACULTY ADVISORS' NOTE













                                                     Dear Readers,

                   ECONP₹ISM is a student-managed newsletter published quarterly by Indira Gandhi
                   Institute of Development Research, Mumbai. The newsletter is envisaged to create
                      awareness about essential work done at our Institute, to act as a platform that
                 showcases academic and non-academic activities of the Institute, and to create synergy

                    between the Institute’s activities and those of other academicians, policymakers,
                                       regulatory bodies and the corporate sector.

                   The broad theme of the current issue is “Covid-19: Impact and Lessons Learnt”. The
                  current issue features regular articles and interviews of senior academicians, reports
                    on the Institute library's activities, reports on the Alumni committee’s activities,

                 summaries of other student initiatives like ‘Kaawish’, and so on. Hence, we feel that this
                     issue contains a good mix of expert articles on the broad theme and the internal
                                                activities of the institute.

                  We would like to extend our heartfelt gratitude to the Director, the Dean of Students,
                   the Registrar, and the members of the Newsletter sub-committee for their guidance
                  and support. We would also like to take this opportunity to thank the contributors for

                 taking out their valuable time to provide articles for this issue. Lastly, we would like to
                  acknowledge the exemplary contributions of this issue’s student editors, design team,
                     and volunteers, who during these difficult times, worked with a lot of focus and
                           dedication to get quality articles for this edition of the newsletter.


                  We hope that readers would enjoy going through this issue of the newsletter. We wish
                 to engage and encourage more academicians, policymakers, and alumni of this institute
                                    to share their contributions to our future issues.

                                                      Best wishes,
                                Dr. Bharti Nandwani and Dr. Gopakumar Achuthankutty,
                                             Faculty Advisors, ECONP₹ISM













                                                                                                                 5
                                                                                                                  5]]></page><page Index="9"><![CDATA[ARTICLES FROM



                                          EXPERTS


















                                                 ONE YEAR OF COVID-19 AND
        ONE YEAR OF

        COVID-19 AND THE                                THE INDIAN ECONOMY
        INDIAN ECONOMY
                                                                  DR. S. MAHENDRA DEV

            - by Dr. S. Mahendra Dev
                                                 The evolution of cooking styles
                                                 One of the topics for this newsletter is the impact and lessons of
                                                 Covid-19. I would like to discuss here Covid-19 and its impact on
                                                 Delivering newsletters through email is one of the best
                                                 the  Indian  economy,  lessons  learnt  and  the  policies  needed  to
         GET BY WITH A                           ways to build a strong relationship with your members and
         LITTLE HELP FROM                        improve  growth,  jobs  and  equity.  The  coronavirus  pandemic
                                                 customers. Give them exclusive access to your latest
         FRIENDS (AND                            which  is  a  once  in  a  century  event  has  affected  both  lives  and
                                                 collections, services, and limited offers while
                                                 livelihoods in the last one year. The economic crisis that we are
         SHOPKEEPERS):                           simultaneously improving  the visibility of your brand. No
                                                 facing today is vastly different from any crisis that we have seen
         HOUSEHOLD                               need to limit yourself to brochures or billboards. With a
                                                 recently. This is the first economic crisis in recent memory that
         BORROWING IN                            simple click, clients can be up-to-date on your newest and
                                                 has been triggered by a non-economic factor- ‘a pandemic'.
         RESPONSE TOCOVID-                       biggest releases at home, work, and even while traveling.
         19                                      What is the impact on Indian Economy?
                                                 Email newsletters can also help you grow your company.
              - by Dr. Ajay Shah &               The  pandemic  has  inflicted  two  shocks:  a  health  shock  and  an
               Dr. Renuka Sane                   After all, it only takes a few seconds for relevant
                                                 economic  shock.  On  health,  India  has  11.8  million  corona  cases
                                                 information to reach your clients. That's why it's important
                                                 with  1.61  lakh  deaths  by  the  end  of  March  2021.  The  overall
                                                 to have engaging content that will keep them subscribed
                                                 fatality rate is 1.36 and it is considered one of the lowest across
                                                 for years to come. Add your logos, photos, and other brand
                                                 the  countries.  Vaccination  drive  started  from  January,  2021.
         COVID-19: THE                           materials to make sure everything is clean and consistent.
         INVISIBLE VICIOUS                       Cumulatively  India  has  administered  around  6.5  crore  vaccine
                                                 doses till the end of March, 2021. From April 1, vaccinations also
         FOE
                                                 started for the age group 45-60. The second wave of Covid-19 is

            - by Dr. Namrata Gulati              expected given the recent spike in corona virus cases. Therefore,
                 &   Chandni Nanda               it is a biggest health shock for India since independence.


                                                 The economic shock has been much more severe for India, for



                                                                                                                 6]]></page><page Index="10"><![CDATA[two reasons. First, pre-COVID-19, the economy was already slowing down, compounding existing

           problems of unemployment, low incomes, rural distress, malnutrition, and widespread inequality.
           Second, India’s large informal sector is particularly vulnerable. Out of the national total 465 million
           workers, around 91% (422 million) were informal workers in 2017-18.


           The economic shock has impacted both formal and informal sectors. The growth slowdown of the
           Indian economy during the pre Covid-19 period was mostly due to insufficient growth of demand.
           During  the  pandemic  time,  both  demand  and  supply  were  affected.  On  the  demand  side,

           consumption, investment and exports have been subdued. Domestic and global supply disruptions
           have led to supply side problems in many sectors. There have been massive disruptions in global
           production supply chains, tourism and trade.
           The problem of twin balance sheet has been accentuated further with more stress in corporate and
           financial sectors. The MSME sector has been badly hit by the reduced cash flows. In the banking
           sector,  NPAs  are  likely  to  increase  for  all  the  scheduled  commercial  banks,  NBFCs  (non-banking

           finance companies) and micro finance institutions. The NPAs could be much more for retail loans.
           There has been a disconnect between stock market and real sector performance. Agriculture is the
           only sector which showed a positive growth of 3% to 3.5% in 2020-21


           The lockdown has choked off almost all economic activity. But, the worst affected are the bottom of
           the pyramid particularly the informal workers including migrants. In urban areas, the pandemic
           has led to the widespread losses of jobs and incomes for informal workers and the poor. Estimates

           by the Centre for Monitoring Indian Economy (CMIE) show that unemployment shot up from 8.4%
           in  mid-March  to  23%  in  the  first  week  of  April.  There  are  about  40-50  million  seasonal  migrant
           workers in India. Media have broadcast images of hundreds of thousands of migrant workers from
           several states trudging for miles and miles on highways. The shutdown has caused untold misery
           for  informal  workers  particularly  the  migrants  who  lead  precarious  lives  facing  hunger  and

           malnutrition. Lacking regular salaries or incomes, these agriculture, migrant, and other informal
           workers were the hardest-hit during the lockdown period.


           The  second  advanced  estimates  show  that  India’s  real  GDP  would  decline  by  8%  in  2020-21  as
           compared to 2019-20. Some projections show the real GDP would increase by 10% to 11% in 2021-22.
           If we look at the levels, the real GDP in 2019-20 was Rs.145.7 trillion while it is expected to decline
           to  Rs.134.1  trillion  in  2020-21.  Even  if  we  have  10%  growth,  the  level  of  GDP  would  be  Rs.  147.5
           trillion in 2021-22 – this is only 1.1% higher than the level of 2019-20.

           According to CMIE, the employment rate is still 2.5 percentage points lower now as compared to
           the  level  before  the  lockdown  last  year.  Women  lost  more  jobs  and  many  were  out  of  the
           workforce. Inequalities increased in health care and education.


           What is the response of the government?

           The  Central  government  announced  a  comprehensive  economic  relief  package  called  the
           ‘Atmanirbhar (self-sufficient) package which had three components: (i) monetary actions; (b) fiscal
           actions; (c) economic reforms. The announcements were made in the months of March, May and
           November in 2020. The Centre and the Reserve Bank of India (RBI) have together provided total
           fiscal stimulus of Rs. 29.87 lakh crore since the Covid-19 pandemic began. This amount is 15% of


                                                                                                                   7]]></page><page Index="11"><![CDATA[India’s  GDP.  RBI  announced  liquidity  and             reconstruction  company.  Fourth,  there  is  no
      measures worth of Rs. 12.71 lakh crore till the end       additional tax in the budget. The expenditure will
      of The  government  package  consists  of  measures       be   borrowed     from     market    or   through

      for the poor and vulnerable groups, health, MSMEs         disinvestment. Fifth, there is some push to health
      (micro,    small    and    medium      enterprises),      sector.
      agriculture, manufacturing etc. It also includes the
      much  debated  agriculture  reforms  which  became        What  are  the  lessons  learnt  and  policies
      three  farm  laws  later.  On  manufacturing,  under      needed  to  improve  growth,  equity  and
      Atmanirbhar  3.0,  government  announced  Rs.  1.45
                                                                employment?
      lakh  crores  production  linked  incentive  scheme
                                                                There are several lessons on different sectors due
      for 10 champion sectors.
                                                                to  the  pandemic.  First  lesson  is  on  health  sector.
                                                                Central  and  state  governments  can  tackle  the
      Apart from the Central government, several state
                                                                current ‘second wave’ better than the ‘first wave’
      governments       have     initiated    innovative
                                                                of  corona  virus  because  of  the  experience.  We
      programmes to help the informal workers and the
                                                                need to improve India’s health sector at different
      unemployed poor. Kerala government for example
                                                                levels including states and districts. Second lesson
      has announced a Rs. 20,000 crore package.
                                                                is on lockdown. Initially, lockdown was needed to
                                                                prepare for taking care of the infected patients. It
      There  are  some  good  things  in  the  recent  Union
                                                                had  adverse  impact  on  livelihoods  although  it
      budget  2021-22.  First,  it  is  transparent  on  fiscal
                                                                might have saved lives. But, overtime, it is viewed
      deficit numbers by including the earlier off-budget
                                                                that  lockdown  is  not  the  solution  for  controlling
      numbers. Second, budget has given push to capital
                                                                the  pandemic.  The  country  has  to  live  with  the
      expenditure      and     infrastructure.    Capital
                                                                pandemic     by   following   covid    appropriate
      expenditure  increased  from  Rs.4.1  lakh  crore  in
                                                                behaviour without lockdowns for quite some time.
      this  year  budget  to  Rs.5.5  lakh  crore  next  year
      budget  (around  35%  increase).  Further  Rs.  2  lakh
                                                                Third  lesson  is  on  education.  Online  education  is
      crore  of  capital  expenditure  were  allotted  for
                                                                not efficient one as compared teaching physically
      states  and  autonomous  bodies  to  utilize.  Budget
                                                                in  the  classrooms.  There  is  also  digital  divide  in
      also  announced  a  DFI,  development  financial
                                                                education  between  haves  and  have  nots.  Even
      institution  to  promote  investment.  Third,  the
                                                                those who have computers and other equipment,
      budget  made  directional  change  with  reforms:
                                                                connectivity is a serious problem in many areas of
      asset  monetization,  privatization  of  banks,  FDI
                                                                India. Fourth one is on work from home. It is not a
      increase in insurance, setting up of asset
                                                                problem  for  those  who  have  relatively  bigger
                                                                houses  to  work  from  home.  The  houses  are  too
                                                                small to work from home for the middle class and
                                                                the  lower  middle  classes.  The  poor  and  informal

                                                                workers including gig workers can’t afford to stay
                                                                at home unlike the privileged organized workers.
                                                                Lastly,  one  big  lesson  is  on  migrant  workers.
                                                                During  the  pandemic  time,  the  government  and
                                                                the  employers  should  take  care  of  the  migrants.
                                                                There  is  also  need  to  protect  the  rights  of
                                                                migrants. We need to put in place safety nets for

                                                                them.
                                                                Turning to the economy, several policies are

                                                                                                                 8]]></page><page Index="12"><![CDATA[needed to improve growth, equity including jobs. Some of the economic reforms announced may help in
       reviving growth in the next few years by raising  investment, reducing the twin balance sheet problem of
       banks  with  NPAs  and  debt  problem  for  the  corporate  sector,  increasing  credit  flow,  solving  supply  side
       problems  and  improving  exports.  However,  we  discuss  here  on  the  policies  needed  for  reducing
       inequalities as we are having ‘K’ shaped recovery.



       Covid-19 in the last one year has once again reminded us the growing inequalities in India. A recent Pew
       Research Report shows that India’s middle class may have shrunk by a third due to the pandemic while the
       number of poor people earning less than Rs.150 per day more than doubled. The Pew report also warned
       that the situation may actually be worse than estimated because of worsening inequalities.


       Inequalities  were  increasing  earlier  also  but  the  pandemic  has  widened  them  further.  For  example,  the

       share of wages declined as compared to that of profits. The big companies and large part of the corporate
       sector could manage the pandemic. The quarterly net profit of the BSE200 companies reached a record high
       of Rs.1.67 trillion in the third quarter of FY21 and was up by 57% year-on-year. But, the informal sector and
       workers have suffered a lot with loss of incomes and employment in the last one year. In other words, the
       recovery is more k-shaped with rising inequalities.



       Development  can’t  be  discussed  without  talking  about  inequality.  In  the  past  several  philosophers,
       economists and other social scientists have discussed about inequality. In recent years. Rising income and
       wealth inequality attracted the attention of IMF, World Bank, OECD and Davos meetings. With the release
       of  the  book  by  French  economist  Thomas  Piketty  in  2014,  there  has  been  more  debate  on  inequality  in
       several  parts  of  the  world.  First  time  at  global  level,  a  goal  on  inequality  is  included  in  sustainable
       Development Goals (SDGs). Goal 10 of SDGs is about reduction in inequality within and among countries.
       There are two main arguments for reduction in inequality. One is ethical or philosophical argument that

       equity is important for its own sake (intrinsic value). Second one is reduction in inequality is required for
       sustainability  of  growth  (instrumental  value).  Therefore,  there  is  a  need  for  addressing  inequality  for
       sustainable growth and well-being.

       As  the  British  economist  Anthony  Atkinson  says
       “much  is  written  about  the  1  per  cent  and  the  99
       per  cent.  But,  if  we  are  serious  about  reducing
       income inequality, what can be done? Reduction in
       inequalities  is  important  for  its  own  sake  and  for
       improving  demand  which  can  raise  private
       investment,  consumption  and  exports  for  higher

       and sustainable economic growth.

                                        SEE BLOG
       We  concentrate  here  on  three-pronged  approach
       for  reducing  inequalities.  These  are:  (a)  focus  on
       employment  and  wages,  (b)  raising  human
       development and (c) Quasi universal basic income

       and other social safety nets.


       First,   creation   of   quality   or   productive
       employment is central to the inclusive growth

                                                                                                                 9]]></page><page Index="13"><![CDATA[39% in 2011-12 to 31.7% in 2018-19 has to be improved. Investment in infrastructure including construction
       can  create  employment.  In  the  recent  budget,  the  central  government  has  rightly  focused  on  capital
       expenditure for infrastructure. There are eight challenges in employment: (a) creating productive jobs for 7
       to  8  million  per  year;  (b)  correcting  the  mismatch  between  demand  and  supply  of  labour:  Only  2.3%  of
       India’s workforce has formal skill training compared to 96% in South Korea, 80% in Japan, and 52% in USA;

       (c)  Structural  change  challenge:  Manufacturing  should  be  the  engine  of  growth.  Here  labour  intensive
       exports are important. Manufacturing and services are complementary; (d) focusing on MSME and informal
       sector including rights of migrants; (e) Getting ready for automation and technology revolution; (f) Social
       security  and  decent  working  conditions  for  all;  (g)  raising  real  wages  of  rural  and  urban  workers  and
       guaranteeing minimum wages.

       Second  one  is  creating  equality  of  opportunity  by  improving  human  development.  Increasing  public

       expenditure  on  health  and  education  is  another  form  of  redistributive  measure.  Covid-19  has  given  us
       several  lessons  on  health  sector.  Public  expenditure  on  health  is  only  1.5  per  cent  of  GDP.  Apart  from
       spending on vaccine and other related measures, we need to move towards universal health care and spend
       2 to 3 per cent of GDP on health. Education and health achievements are essential for reducing inequality of
       opportunities. Great quality dichotomy exists in both these sectors. There are islands of excellence that can

       compete  internationally  in  education  while  vast  majority  of  them  churn  masses  of  children  with  poor
       learning achievement. We also have the experience of digital gap in education during the pandemic. One has
       to fix this dichotomy in health and education.

       The third one is providing quasi universal basic income and other safety nets. For example, Dr. Rangarajan
       and  myself  suggested  three  proposals  on  minimum  income  for  the  poor  and  vulnerable  in  the  post-
       pandemic period. These are: (a) cash transfers to all women above the age of 20 years; (b) expanding the
       number of days provided under MGNREGA (Mahatma Gandhi National Rural Employment Guarantee Act)

       and (c) National employment guarantee scheme for urban areas. In all these proposals, there is no problem
       of identification. A combination of cash transfers and an expanded guarantee scheme can provide income
       support to the needy.
       Apart  from  the  above,  increasing  farmers’  income  particularly  small  and  marginal  farmers  is  needed  for
       reducing inequalities and creating demand. Farmer producer organisations should be strengthened. States

       have to be given more role in agri marketing reforms. Terms of trade for agriculture has to be improved.
        Enhancing tax and non-tax revenues of the government is needed to spend on the above priorities. The
       tax/GDP ratio has to be raised with a wider tax base. Richer sections have to pay more taxes. Similarly, the
       inequalities between Centre and states should be reduced in finances. State budgets must be strengthened
       to improve capital expenditures on physical infrastructure and spending on health, education and social
       safety nets. Apart from economic factors, non-economic factors like deepening democracy, decentralization
       can help in reducing inequalities. Unequal distribution of development is rooted in inequalities of political,

       social and economic power. We have to find opportunities and spaces where the power can be challenged
       and redistributed. In the post-covid world, addressing inequality is important for higher and sustainable
       economic growth and well-being of the population.

                                                                                                                 10]]></page><page Index="14"><![CDATA[GET BY WITH A LITTLE HELP FROM MY

          FRIENDS (AND SHOPKEEPERS): HOUSEHOLD

               BORROWING IN RESPONSE TO COVID 19




                                      AJAY SHAH & RENUKA SANE





       The  lockdown  in  the  early  days  of  the  Covid  19  pandemic  in  India  impacted  on  on  economic  activity.
       Between  April  and  August  2020,  18.9  million  salaried  people  lost  their  jobs,  difficulties  were  faced  by
       migrant labourers, and small and medium businesses. Deshpande (2020) shows that overall employment
       dropped  sharply  post-lockdown,  with  larger  drops  for  women  than  men.  Household  incomes  were

       adversely affected. As an example, survey work by Lee, Sahai, Baylis and Greenstone (2020) shows that two
       months into the lockdown poor and non-migrant workers in Delhi saw a drop of 57% in their incomes, with
       9 out of 10 workers reporting that their weekly income had fallen to zero. Bertrand, Krishnan and Schofield
       (2020) measure the fraction of households who say they are able to survive on their own for a week, and in
       April that value was 34% in the overall population and 50% or more for below-median household income.



       How  would  households  cope  with  such  a  shock?  Economic  theory  suggests  that  households  desire
       consumption smoothing. One mechanism for consumption smoothing is borrowing. For example, there was
       an increase in household borrowing after demonetisation (Karmarkar and Narayan, 2020; Wadhwa, 2019;
       Chakraborty and Sane, 2019). This connects to the working of the financial system. While India has made a
       lot of progress in ownership of a bank account, and increased electronic payments, access to formal credit
       remains low.



       What do we expect about household borrowings?


       Borrowing during the Covid crisis is shaped by three factors:

       1. Income transfers: The government of India announced a stimulus package worth Rs.1.7 trillion after the
       lockdown. This included food security measures as well as direct cash transfers to poor households. This

       may have helped households deal with the immediate crisis.

       2. Low demand: As people were at home owing to the lockdown, demand may have been affected. It is also
       possible that households saw this job loss as permanent, and hence cut back on expenditures in a way they
       would not have had they seen this as a temporary disruption. This also fits with the view that precautionary
       savings increase after a deep crisis (Rajadhyaksha, 2020). However, this may be true for households in the
       higher income distributions, but is unlikely to be the case for those below median income.












                                                                                                                 11]]></page><page Index="15"><![CDATA[3. Supply constraints: India's financial system has faced difficulties since 2012. This has manifested itself as
       business failure at ILFS and other financial firms, large and small. Credit growth was decelerating prior to
       the lockdown. The difficulties for the financial sector increased when the Reserve Bank of India announced
       a moratorium on all loan repayments for three months from March to May 2020, and then extended it for

       another  three  months.  These  moratoriums  made  it  more  difficult  for  financial  firms  to  assess  the  credit
       quality  of  borrowers.  Overall  bank  credit  growth  was  5.8%  in  September  2020  compared  to  8.1%  in
       September 2019. From 2018 onwards, when certain borrowers faced supply constraints, they would have
       had to deleverage (repaying old loans while not getting new ones) or default. The grand question of the field
       consists  of  understanding  the  economic  condition  of  households  in  India  in  2020,  in  examining  how

       consumption was held up through new kinds of labour supply and through borrowing, and in obtaining
       insights into these three distinct economic forces that are in play. In this article, we discover some new
       facts that contribute towards this overall research agenda.


       Methodology


       We source data from the Consumer Pyramids Household Survey (CPHS) for the months of May, June, July

       and August from the years 2016 - 2020. The borrowing data comes from the Aspirational India table within
       CPHS. Using this we ask three questions: 1. Did households have debt outstanding at the time of the survey?
       This  helps  us  understand  the  total  number  of  borrowers  in  the  economy.  2.  What  are  the  sources  from
       whom households have outstanding borrowings? This tells us whether households borrow from the formal
       or the informal sector. 3. What is the purpose for which households have outstanding

       borrowings?  This  tells  us  if  households  are

       borrowing  for  consumption  expenditure,  for
       consumer  durables,  or  for  running  their
       businesses.   CPHS      does    not    provide
       information on the value of debt outstanding.
       We  are,  therefore,  not  able  to  analyse  the
       impact on borrowing on an intensive margin.

       Our analysis is restricted to understanding the
       proportion  of  households  borrowing  from
       various sources, for various reasons, i.e. on the
       extensive margin. Household weights for each
       wave are provided by CPHS -- these are used
                                                                                  Table 1: Number and share of borrowers
       to get population estimates.                                           in the population


       Results: The number of borrowers Table 1 presents the number and percentage of households having debt
       outstanding in the months of May - August in each of the five years. The number of borrower households
       had been consistently increasing till 2019. In May - August 2016, 12% of the population had debt outstanding.

       This increased to 50% by 2019. The number, however, fell in 2020 to 45% of the population. The fall has been
       greater in urban regions than rural.











                                                                                                                12]]></page><page Index="16"><![CDATA[Disentangling explanations: Sources of borrowing


      Given that a large proportion of households did not have enough to live on for more than a couple of weeks,
      we would have expected a huge increase in the number of borrower households. In order to investigate the

      sources  of  this  drop,  we  begin  by  analysing  the  role  of  the  financial  system  in  the  household  borrowing
      story by studying the sources of borrowing.



      Table  2  presents  the  percentage  of  borrower  households  borrowing  from  each  source.  We  find  that  the
      biggest drop in borrowing is from banks: in 2019, 26% of borrower households had borrowed from banks -
      this  has  dropped  to  20%  in  2020.  The  proportion  of  households  borrowing  from  money  lenders  has  also
      dropped - from 7% in 2019 to 4% in 2020. The drop in households borrowing from banks and money lenders
      was  higher  in  urban  regions  than  rural  regions.  There  has  been  a  lot  of  discussion  in  India  about  the

      increased  risk  aversion  of  banks.  A  fall  in  the  number  of  borrower  households  may  be  a  result  of  this
      phenomenon.



















                                                                     Table 2: Sources of borrowing





      There has been a concurrent rise in the number of households who have borrowed from friends and family
      from 14% in 2019 to 21% in rural regions, and from 13% to 27% in urban regions. The sharp increase in the
      borrowing from friends and family suggests that some smoothing of consumption expenditure is likely to
      have occurred using informal social networks that play an important role in the economic lives of those in
      developing countries (Munshi, 2014).



      Household borrowing from shops increased in rural India - from 52% to 58%, and fell slightly in urban India.
      It is interesting to recall that Chakraborty and Sane (2019) had found that between the years 2016 and 2018
      (i.e. after demonetisation), the biggest rise in borrowing was from shops, especially by those in the lower
      income deciles. This seems to be true in the current situation as well, especially in rural regions.


      In difficult times, it was not banks, money lenders, and employers that mattered. It was friends and family,

      and the neighbourhood shops. It appears that non-financial firms and cash flow management by the retail
      supply  chain  have  been  more  important  than  financial  firms.  The  connections  from  the  formal  financial
      system to these shops could then be unusually influential.










                                                                                                                 13]]></page><page Index="17"><![CDATA[Disentangling explanations: Purpose of borrowing



       Examining the purpose for which households borrow can tell us something about the demand for credit.
       Table 3 presents the top five reasons for borrowing in 2020, and compares it with 2019.
       In  May-August  2019,  62%  of  rural  and  60%  of  urban  borrower  households  had  borrowed  for  reasons  of
       consumption expenditure. In May-August 2020, this had risen to 70% and 66% of rural and urban borrower
       households respectively. This is consistent with the importance of consumption smoothing, and of many
       households not having enough resources to survive for more than a few weeks. The increase for reasons of
       consumption expenditure is higher in urban regions. Urban India was more likely to be affected because of

       both the Covid infections and the intensity of the lockdown than rural India. Income transfers from the
       government are also likely to have targeted rural households than urban households.


















                                                                     Table 3: Purpose of borrowing



       There has been an increase in borrowing for business and debt-repayment reasons in this period as well.
       The numbers for rolling over debt went from about 9% to 12% of borrower households in urban regions, and
       from 7% to 9% of borrower households in rural regions. This suggests that households who would otherwise
       have serviced debt through business or personal income took recourse to borrowing when those cashflows
       subsided.  A  personal  insolvency  law  that  is  able  to  provide  some  relief  to  debtors  and  allow  for

       restructuring of the larger loans can help alleviate some of this stress.


       The fall in the number of borrower households seems to be driven by the fall in the borrowings for housing,
       durables purchase and investments. It is also likely that large purchases such as housing and durables are
       made through bank loans. The fall in the borrowings from banks may be a result of a fall in these large
       durable purchases.



       Conclusion


       We study the response of households on borrowings during the 2020 lockdown. We do not have data on the
       value of debt outstanding. We expected that there would be an increase in the number of households that
       borrow  owing  to  the  disruptions  to  economic  activity.  However,  it  is  remarkable,  that  despite  the  large
       shock, overall, there has been a reduction in the number of households that borrow. This fall is driven by

       fewer  households  borrowing  from  banks,  and  fewer  households  borrowing  for  housing,  and  consumer
       durables  purchases.  Households  continue  to  borrow  for  consumption  expenditure,  business  and  debt
       repayment. The most utilised sources of borrowing are friends and family and shops.





                                                                                                                 14]]></page><page Index="18"><![CDATA[This work suggests many interesting possibilities for downstream research. For example, one can study the

       differences in borrowing patterns between households with different income and wealth profiles, as well as
       the  correlation  between  sources  and  purpose  of  borrowing.  It  will  also  be  possible  to  evaluate  whether
       income transfers from the government led to a fall in the number of borrower households. Similarly, one
       can ask whether different health outcomes play a role in their borrowing outcomes.


       The  number  of  households  choosing  to  borrow  has  been  different  from  what  happened  after
       demonetisation. There may be several reasons for this - the magnitude of the disruption, the length of time

       for which it lasted, the possibility of more permanent impacts on labour markets among others. This leaves
       us  with  interesting  research  possibilities  to  understand  household  behaviour  and  their  interaction  with
       financial markets.


       References



       Ashwini  Deshpande  (2020),  The  Covid-19  Pandemic  and  Lockdown:  First  Effects  on  Gender  Gaps  in
       Employment and Domestic Work in India, Working Paper 30, Ashoka University.
       Azim  Premji  University  (2019),  "State  of  Working  India  2019",  Technical  Report,  Centre  for  Sustainable
       Employment.
       Kaivan  Munshi  (2014),  "Community  Networks  and  the  Process  of  Development",  Journal  of  Economic
       Perspectives, 28(4), pp: 49-76.
       Kenneth Lee, Harshil Sahai, Patrick Baylis, and Michael Greenstone (2020), "Job Loss and Behavioral Change:

       The Unprecedented Effects of the India Lockdown in Delhi", Working Paper, EPIC India.
       Marianne Bertrand, Kaushik Krishnan, and Heather Schofield (2020), "How are Indian households coping
       under  the  COVID-19  lockdown?  8  key  findings",  Rustandy  Centre  for  Social  Sector  Innovation,  Chicago
       Booth.
       Niranjan Rajadhyaksha (2020), "The covid shock could alter people's financial priorities", Livemint, 5 May

       2020.
       Sagar Wadhwa (2019), "Impact of demonetization on household consumption in India, Working paper.
       Subhamoy Chakraborty and Renuka Sane (2019), "Household debt over time", The Leap Blog, 24 May 2019.
       Sudipto  Karmarkar  and  Abhinav  Narayanan  (2020),  "Do  households  care  about  cash?  Exploring  the
       heterogeneous effects of India's demonetization", Journal of Asian Economics, 69.





       Sane is a researcher at the National Institute of Public Finance and Policy, Shah is an independent scholar.
       We  thank  four  anonymous  referees,  Kaushik  Krishnan,  Radhika  Pandey  and  Anjali  Sharma  for  useful
       comments.


       (Republished from The Leap Blog)
















                                                                                                                 15]]></page><page Index="19"><![CDATA[COVID-19 THE


                                INVISIBLE VICIOUS FOE




                                NAMRATA GULATI & CHANDNI NANDA




       Covid-19 has affected our lives in a way never before. It has touched us in many unprecedented ways, far
       beyond what we could imagine. When it first invaded our territory, we were complacent and perhaps many

       of us refused to even acknowledge its arrival. We did not give to it the attention it was seeking. Slowly and
       steadily,  it  started  spreading  its  tentacles  and  made  everyone  acknowledge  that;  we  can’t  trivialize  its
       existence. Soon everyone was engulfed in fear that this invisible and potentially invincible enemy might
       embrace us anywhere, and we may not even get to know about it. This fear was there amongst everyone;
       rich or poor, male or female, child or adult. It assaulted everyone with equal dignity without discriminating
       on the basis of caste, religion, gender, or wealth. This virus was completely oblivious of the deep-rooted

       differences in human society which have prevailed for ages.


       But we were differently prepared to defend ourselves from this onslaught. We all started taking refuge in
       our shelters to guard ourselves, and our near and dear ones. Some of us, called upon the inner strength and
       courage to face the challenge. Some of us were more materially resourceful to withstand the attack and
       refused  to  be  trampled  by  the  unseen  foe.  Depending  upon  both  our  external  and  internal  wealth  and
       wisdom, we made a conscious decision not to wander in the unknown terrain where this enemy was more

       dominating – like the overcrowded place. But many were overpowered by the circumstances. They had no
       liberty to make choices –which could save them, keep their families secure or make them stronger. Apart
       from this tangible external attack on health, this enemy was quietly seeking to change the way we conduct
       our  lives.  The  entire  economic  machinery  was  up  for  a  toss.  The  deep-rooted  human  relations  were
       challenged.



       But, all of us were willing to take on the fight and were reluctant to give up so easily. Many of us had to
       make  adjustments  which  we  could  never  think  of,  but  we  were  ready  for  this  fierce  battle  not  just  for
       ourselves but also for the sake of those whom we held close in our hearts. We also felt the presence of an
       unseen force that was binding us together and making us more empathetic. We took this as an opportunity
       to serve others.


       Given our uniqueness, each one of us had a different tale to share about the sacrifices we made and the

       changes we accepted. A story that varied depending upon our internal strength, the courage we derived
       from our relations, from our resources, and from the agencies which were around to help us out.
       Who  are  the  people  who  emerged  undefeated?  What  were  the  factors  which  played  a  critical  role  in
       announcing their victory? How did the external agency help those who were not strong enough to defend
       themselves? Was the help granted equitable or some people, based on caste, creed, and gender victim of

       some form of prejudice? How effective was this external support? Did this unseen






                                                                                                                 16]]></page><page Index="20"><![CDATA[rival – without any intention, exasperate the existing difference which has prevailed in the society? Did it
       increase the differences between rich and poor and if yes, then how? Or did it provide opportunities to

       those  who  were  underprivileged?  Did  females,  who  have  been  traditionally  victimized  -showed  greater
       resilience  during  this  pandemic?  The  answers  to  these  questions  are  not  so  simple  and  straight.  Many
       factors played a critical role. No matter how hard we try, we may not be able to do complete justice to all
       potential theories. But even if we are not able to thoroughly apprehend and appreciate the role of different
       channels, still it’s worthwhile to make a small attempt in this direction. We first try to list down different
       dimensions in which our lives have been affected. None of the aspects is less important than the other, and
       each merits a detailed understanding.



       To complement our hypothesis and to better untangle the linkages, we used the data collected by Young
       Lives.  The  data  has  been  collected  for  four  countries:  India,  Ethiopia,  Peru,  and  Vietnam.  This  data  was
       collected using a phone survey rather usually conducted than face-to-face surveys due to the onset of this
       pandemic.



       The total sample used for India were 2000 children from the Younger Cohort (YC), i.e., those who were born
       in  2001-02,  and  the  rest  1000  children  from  the  Older  Cohort  (YC)  who  born  in  1994-95  from  Andhra
       Pradesh  and  Telangana.  In  the  first  phone  call  (between  June  2020  to  July  2020),  a  total  of  2,750  young
       people (1,863 of Younger Cohort respondents aged 18, and 887 Older Cohort respondents aged 25 years old)
       were questioned. The idea of this survey was to gauge the individual’s understanding of the pandemic.



       In  the  second  call  (between  August  2020  to  October  2020),  a  total  of  2,754  young  people  (1,868  Younger
       Cohort respondents aged 18, and 886 Older Cohort respondents aged 25) were questioned. This time the
       focus was primarily to look at the impact of Covid-19 on the labour market, education, and health of people.

       Now, we come back to pertinent questions that this pandemic has raised. Who were the people who were
       most affected by the virus in terms of their mental health? Was this enemy able to play on the individual's

       vulnerabilities and pose a more emotional threat to one set of people relative to the others?
       Did the adversaries that women faced right from their birth make them better prepared to take up the
       challenge?  Or  were  they  subjected  to  more  torment  because  of  the  increased  burden  of  the  household
       chores and taking care of children?


       From  the  data,  we  have  created  an  anxiety  score  which  can  take  a  value  from  0  to  9,  a  higher  value
       reflecting a higher value of anxiety. From the graph labelled "Mean Anxiety by Gender", it is evident that

       the mean level of anxiety was higher for females relative to males. The possible reason for it, as validated
       by the data, was the increased burden of household chores and taking care of children. A larger proportion
       of females concurred that there was an increase in the time spent in taking care of child care. Similarly,
       around 60 per cent of females agreed that the burden of the household chores increased. It's pertinent to
       note that an already huge percentage of women are overwhelmed by household responsibilities and are

       operating at the threshold level. Any addition to that load would greatly exhaust them.












                                                                                                                17]]></page><page Index="21"><![CDATA[18]]></page><page Index="22"><![CDATA[Next, we seek to compare the stress level amongst people belonging to different age groups. Were children
       left more perturbed due to the restriction on their freedom or were they more relaxed than before as had
       more time to bond with their parents, grandparents, and siblings? Were old left more anxious because of the
       looming threat of falling sick easily and taking longer to recover?



       Depending on the age, we had divided people into 4 groups. ‘Young child’ were those who were below 15
       years old. Between 15 and 30 were categorized as ‘Young’; 30 – 55 as ‘middle-aged’ and anyone above 55 were
       categorized as ‘old’. From the data, we find that the stress level was highest amongst young child and old
       relative to the other categories.






























       The income level of the household is also a very important determinant of their level of stress. Were poor
       now made more conscious of their deprivation as many had to continue to go out to seek work to sustain
       their families? They, unlike their rich counterpart, did not have the luxury to switch to the online platform.
       The following graph laid credence to the theories proposed and we find that the mean anxiety increased

       with the material deprivation of the household.






                                                                                                                19]]></page><page Index="23"><![CDATA[Next, the critical issue that we would like to focus on is the gap between rich and poor. Here again, there are

       many  dimensions,  and  all  are  vital  components  in  explaining  the  change  in  gap.  First,  let’s  talk  about
       students.  All  students,  especially  the  younger  ones,  were  given  online  instructions.  But  the  poor  were
       constrained because of the lack of resources to receive lessons. Whereas people who were on the other end
       of the income spectrum could arrange for the tailor-made private tuitions at home, and this was over and
       above the formal training that they were receiving from their educational institution.


       It is evident from the graph labeled; "Reason for not attending the class by Household Type", that it was the

       poor who were scared badly. Many of them had to give up on education because of the lack of resources.


       The pandemic gave a choice to work from home to those who were resourceful and skilled, but the others
       who  were  already  less  privileged  people  were  left  without  work.  At  times,  for  the  sake  of  meeting  basic
       needs for their families they were forced to take up jobs which increased the threat of their getting infected
       by the virus and transmitting it to their families.



       However, not just poor but even the well-off people experienced the loss of job. Maybe, many businesses
       were left unviable and had to be shut because of lack of demand. In fact, according to the data, people who
       thought that they were highly well-off reported a higher percentage of job loss compared to the others.








                                                                                                                 20]]></page><page Index="24"><![CDATA[21]]></page><page Index="25"><![CDATA[The other subtle effect that the pandemic had was on the prices of commodities and goods and services.
       Because of the lack of supply, certain essential items became scarce leading to an increase in prices. This
       increase in price for the same good varied from one location to the other. The places which had a higher
       concentration of the rich experienced higher increase in the prices – because of the higher willingness to
       pay  of  those  who  were  better-off,  making  the  more  vulnerable  ones  worse-off.  The  following  graph
       highlights the differences in the different regions:
















































       We see that more than 50 per cent of the people residing in the urban region said that they had experienced
       an  increase  in  prices.  Making  a  similar  comparison  between  people  belonging  to  different  income
       categories,  we  find,  that  the  people  who  identified  themselves  as  belonging  to  the  struggling  category
       reported  the  highest  increase  in  prices.  Even  rich  people  reported  an  increase  in  the  prices.  The  only
       income category where the higher percentage reported no increase in prices was those who were very rich.



       Covid-19  also  completely  altered  how  the  labour  market  functions  –  it  made  some  sectors  and  some
       economic activities gain whereas there were many sectors whose existence was completely nullified. No
       amount of intervention was good enough to mitigate the mighty impact of the pandemic.


       As  time  will  pass,  other  significant  ways  in  which  individuals  and  the  economy  has  been  affected  will
       become evident. And, there will be many more ways in which the virus will continue to affect our lives

       which will get revealed only with time. But yes, we do all concede that it was one demon that had potential
       much greater than we could realize We see that more than 50 per cent of the people residing in the urban
       region said that they had experienced an increase in prices. Making a similar comparison between people
       belonging to different income categories, we find, that the people who identified




                                                                                                                  22]]></page><page Index="26"><![CDATA[themselves as belonging to the struggling category reported the highest increase in prices. Even rich people
       reported  an  increase  in  the  prices.  The  only  income  category  where  the  higher  percentage  reported  no
       increase in prices was those who were very rich.



       Covid-19  also  completely  altered  how  the  labour  market  functions  –  it  made  some  sectors  and  some
       economic activities gain whereas there were many sectors whose existence was completely nullified. No
       amount of intervention was good enough to mitigate the mighty impact of the pandemic.


       As  time  will  pass,  other  significant  ways  in  which  individuals  and  the  economy  has  been  affected  will
       become  evident.  And,  there  will  be  many  more  ways  in  which  the  virus  will  continue  to  affect  our  lives

       which will get revealed only with time. But yes, we do all concede that it was one demon that had potential
       much greater than we could realize










































        Acknowledgement:


        The  data  used  in  this  publication  come  from  Young  Lives,  a  15-year  study  of  the  changing  nature  of
        childhood  poverty  in  Ethiopia,  India  (Andhra  Pradesh  and  Telangana),  Peru  and  Vietnam
        (www.younglives.org.uk). Young Lives is core-funded by UK aid from the Department for International

        Development (DFID). The views expressed here are those of the author(s). They are not necessarily those
        of Young Lives, the University of Oxford, DFID or other funders.


        Namrata Gulati is a professor at South Asian University. Chandni Nanda has recently received a Master's
        degree in Economics from Shiv Nadar University and has helped in compiling the graphs.










                                                                                                                 23]]></page><page Index="27"><![CDATA[In




                                                              Conversation





                                                             with Dr. Srijit




                                                                       Mishra





                                                       Q1. For us, the last year has been a year full
                                                       of  transitions  and  adaptations  –  to  new
     P R O F E S S O R   A T   I G I D R               technology, to a new world and to a new life,
                                                       as  a  whole.  What  has  been  your  experience

          He has served as Director                    of life in the past one year? I mean what are
         at NCDS, Bhubaneswar and                      the  realizations  and  challenges  that  the

           also worked as the ICCR                     pandemic has revealed to you?

           Chair Professor of Indian                   It was both good and bad. Thankfully I didn't have to travel
           Studies at NCCU, Taiwan.                    and  relocate  when  the  pandemic  was  at  its  peak.  About

              He has also been an                      adapting  to  the  situation,  currently,  I  am  teaching
         International Guest Scholar                   Contemporary  issues  in  Human  Development  and  Policy
          at Meiji University, Japan                   through a virtual medium. I had my own inhibitions about
                                                       how  the  course  would  move  ahead,  as  my  approach  is
           and a Subir Chowdhury                       generally  interactive.  I  like  to  ask  questions  and  get
            Fellow on Quality and                      feedback.  My  teaching  progress  is  dependent  on  the
          Economics at LSE, London.                    responses  I  get.    Now,  as  I  am  completing  this  course,  I

         He has also been a member                     sense  that  it  has  gone  reasonably  well.  Challenges  like
           of numerous committees                      power-cuts, network issues, etc. have of course been part
             under Government of                       of it. But, we need to get used to such uncertainties. If one

           India. His research area                    can  find  answers  to  the  question  on  how  to  deal  with
               includes Applied                        uncertainty, it would be rewarding as one can then move
           Development Economics                       on to the next phase of life with an ability to handle such

               (Agriculture/Rural                      situations.
            Development, Human                         Q2.  Do  you  think  that  online  teaching  is  a

                 Development,                          solution      in    the     pandemic         given     the
                Measurement of                         infrastructure  India  has?  What  are  your
           Development Indicators,                     thoughts on this and what measures do you
          Public Health and related                    suggest to make the transition better?

           issues), Public Policy and
                 Game Theory.

                                                                                                                 24]]></page><page Index="28"><![CDATA[I  think  institutes  with  lesser  student           difficult  in  a  pandemic  situation.  Some
             strength  or/and  those  with  better                 online  forms  and  telephonic  surveys
             infrastructure  can  address  technological           (including video formats) have come up,
             issues  better.  For  example,  if  students          but  they  cannot  substitute  for  physical
             faced  difficulties  at  IGIDR,  one  could           presence.  Besides,  the  question  of
             provide a laptop, send materials by email             sampling  design  in  the  absence  of
             or upload recorded classes.                           population listing raises other questions.
             When  one  thinks  of  rural  areas,  the             I will take a digression and discuss some
             challenges  increase.  They  may  either              of my fieldwork conducted in the past.
             have  no  access  to  network  connections;
             or  may  be  in  a  family  that  has  a  single      Back  in  2005-06,  at  IGIDR,  we  carried
             phone  for  all  family  members.  The                out  this  study  on  farmers’  suicide  in
             solution  to  this  has  to  be  situation            Maharashtra.  Statistically,  suicide  is  a
             specific.  I  recall  having  read  how  a            rare  event.  Our  list  of  incidences
             teacher  in  a  remote  village  put  down            superimposed to a map indicated that on
             lessons in the walls facing the streets so            an  average  there  was  only  one  instance
             that  students  can  read  them  when  they           of death by suicide in a 30-40 kilometre
             pass  by.  In  another  instance,  the  school        radius. Hence, one cannot design a study
             used its public announcement system to                of  selecting  a  few  villages,  listing  the
             impart  lessons.  In  such  times,  decision          population  of  these  villages  and  then
             making  at  the  local  level  helps  improve         drawing  a  sample.  Our  sample  design
             access to learning.                                   covered  more  than  110  villages.  In  each
             NCERT started an initiative of recording              village,  we  surveyed  the  household
             lectures  and  telecasting  them  through             where  death  by  suicide  occurred,
             their  designated  television  channels.              selected  a  control  household,  discussed
             There  have  been  civil  society  initiatives        with  knowledgeable  people  and  held  a
             to bridge the digital divide by providing             focus  group  discussion  to  have  an
             mobile  phones/tablets  to  students  to              understanding  of  the  socioeconomic
             access  learning  materials.  A  mix  and             scenario. The team also had to be trained
             match  approach  with  technology  and                to handle matters sensitively. The reason
             local-level  initiatives  to  ensure  that            I  am  bringing  this  here  is  to  point  out
             everyone  has  access  to  resources  for             that  the  situation  made  us  innovate
             learning should be the way forward.                   survey  tools  and  designs.  It  is  another
                                                                   matter  that  the  report  led  to  important
             Q3. How do you think the work                         policy decisions by the state and central
                                                                   governments.
             of  data  collection  has  changed
             due  to  the  pandemic?  What  is                     In  spite  of  its  policy  impact,  a  friendly
             the        way        forward         for             academic  critic  once  asked,  “Did  the
             researchers in this regard?                           farmers  benefit  finally?”  This  led  me  to
                                                                   civil  society  organizations  who  work
                                                                   with  farmers  to  develop  research
             Some of you would be pursuing a career                protocols  that  document  evidences.  In
             in research. In certain domains of applied            2015, when I joined NCDS, we submitted
             development research, fieldwork is very               a  proposal  of  collaborative  action
             important. One should understand what                 research to the Government of Odisha to
             is happening at the the ground level. But,            revive cultivation of millets, a nutritious
             this will be                                          and climate resilient crop, in






                                                                                                               25]]></page><page Index="29"><![CDATA[tribal areas. The programme started in 2017 and included four verticals: increase production
              through  new  agronomic  practices,  facilitate  processing  units,  develop  marketing  channels,
              and  revive  consumption  including  their  inclusion  under  supplementary  nutrition
              programmes.  This  being  an  action  research,  an  essential  requirement  is  obtaining  regular
              feedback from different stakeholders – farmers, consumers, civil society functionaries, and
              staff  of  line  department  of  government  among  others.  In  the  initial  days  of  the  pandemic,
              with the first phase of lockdown, all this completely stopped. More importantly, colleagues,
              across the board, got involved in COVID-19 related work. Subsequently, some attempts were
              made through telephonic interviews and online meetings to get some feedback. This paved
              the way to articulate a case to consider workers involved in agricultural activities are also
              like workers involved in public utilities. This was helpful for agriculture in general, but also
              for the millets initiative. By the time I left NCDS in early September of 2020, more than one
              lakh farmers were associated in the programme through the production vertical.

              In economics, we have been trained to incorporate learnings from statistics and mathematics,
              but when it comes to fieldwork we also take lessons from anthropology. Or, as they say, “Go
              and soil your dresses.” That means, go and be part of the people that you are trying to study.
              That is always helpful.

              In fact, in the human development course, a component of fieldwork exists and I am happy to
              state that some of the students in the current batches who have opted for this course provide
              us some important lessons of conducting fieldwork during this ongoing pandemic. Some of
              them conducted face to face interviews, if situation permitted, but in most cases it was done
              virtually. They have a rich repository of cases of the people they see around (such as vendors,
              teachers, comparing public sector versus private sector professionals, people who lost jobs or
              had  a  cut  in  salary,  and  women  who  have  to  balance  between  their  on-line  work  and
              increased domestic responsibility) and how has the pandemic affected their lives.


              The  pandemic  also  strengthened  collaboration  of  researchers  with  network  of  civil  society
              members  or  teachers  of  schools/colleges  in  local  areas  to  document  the  return  of  migrant
              workers  across  the  country,  which  has  led  to  a  number  of  publications  by  scholars  from
              across the country. There is an increasing use of social media to not only elicit responses on
              one’s  questionnaire,  but  also  to  use  that  medium  as  one’s  field  location,  that  is,  to  be  a
              participant observer of a forum that one is a member of. There are scholars who did some
              fieldwork between the two spikes and are following up subsequently through a virtual mode.

              What  one  foresees  is  that  fieldwork  is  increasingly  going  to  be  a  combination  of  physical-
              cum-virtual  mediums,  more  use  of  technology  even  when  one  is  conducting  physical
              fieldwork, and a greater possibility of collaboration with local facilitators including perhaps
              school  children  who  may  get  a  first-hand  exposure  to  research.  Besides,  documenting  the
              change in the method and medium of fieldwork could also be an important area of study.

              I paraphrase Jean Drèze who, as you all know, is one of the foremost development economists
              in India. He had once remarked that one day’s fieldwork is equivalent to six months of library
              work. The field is indeed a very intriguing space and in fact, lot of theoretical and analytical
              observations can come from the field. I would suggest that those of you who are interested in
              doing  research,  even  when  you  are  working  in  the  corporate  world  as  a  researcher,  be
              familiar with your field - whatever that field may be.





                                                                                                                 26]]></page><page Index="30"><![CDATA[Q4.  We  have  seen  that  this                       One  can  bring  in  other  aspects  of
             pandemic  has  brought  out  in                       inequality  like  caste,  class,  gender,  and
             the  open  a  lot  of  inherent                       regional differences among others. Each
                                                                   of  them  is  equally  relevant  and
             developmental             inequalities                important and we need to address them.
             between  the  poor  and  the                          These    kinds     of   challenges    are
             ultra-rich.  It  has  deepened                        continuous: today, you may address one

             inequality        in      terms        of             kind of problem, and, tomorrow, another
             education,        healthcare        and               kind  of  problem  might  emerge.  We
                                                                   should  be  sensitive  to  such  new
             other  basic  necessities.  What                      dimensions  of  inequality  and  explore
             are  your  thoughts  about  this                      possibilities of addressing them.
             and  how  can  we  fight  this

             inequality  as  a  nation  or  even                   I recall Mahatma Gandhi’s talisman, one
                                                                   of his most powerful social philosophies
             as a global citizen?                                  that  he  shared  with  us  a  couple  of

             I think these are important challenges for            months  before  his  death.  He  said  that
             us. These inequalities can be in multiple             whenever  in  doubt,  think  of  the  most
             domains.  First,  we  should  understand              vulnerable person that you have in mind
             how and where they are. Then, we have                 and  then  you  think  about  the  decision
             to  engage  at  multiple  levels.  One  thing         that  you  are  going  to  take.  If  this
             which I have been thinking about in the               decision will be of some help to this most
             last  couple  of  weeks  is  that  this               vulnerable  person,  then  all  your  doubts
             engagement with the market needs to be                will melt away. Ambedkar, who also had
             substantial  for  the  people  who  are  left         the vulnerable in his thinking, gave us a
             out. Let me elaborate on what I mean by               very  civilized  way  of  addressing  such
             that. For instance, if there is a player with         concerns  through  debates,  discussions,
             a  substantial  market  share  then  this             and  evidence-based  reasoning  that  the
             player  will  be  at  an  advantageous                parliamentary  form  of  democracy  gives
             position  both  as  a  buyer  and  as  a  seller.     us.  One  doesn't  have  to  be  violent  to
             But,  at  the  same  time,  smaller  entities         articulate  one’s  case.  I  think  these  are
             cannot  have  that  bargaining  leverage.  It         important  lessons  that  both  of  them
             is for this that those who work with the              have  given  us  and  we  can  use  them  to
             vulnerable  at  the  grassroots  to  address          address these inequalities.
             inequality,  also  need  to  work  towards
             strengthening  the  market  share  of  the
             vulnerable.                                           Q5.  We  know  that  the  one  of
                                                                   the biggest tragedies of 2020 in
             Besides, a      large  number  of  buyers  and        India,  apart  from  the  health
             sellers,  as  some  argue,  can  lead  to  fair
             prices  because  no  one  player  is                  crisis caused by Covid has been
             influencing  them.  Now,  if  one  player  is         the sufferings that the migrant
             able  to  influence  prices  then  that  could        labourers  had  gone  through.
             lead  to  substantial  inequality.  A  case  in       And they are an integral part of
             point, without getting into the scientific            our     metropolitan         economy.
              merit behind the evolving and complex
             science, is the pricing of vaccination and            And this migrant labor crisis is
             related concerns.                                     still a visible reality in 2021 ......






                                                                                                                 27]]></page><page Index="31"><![CDATA[....  which  proves  that  we  haven't  done  anything  substantial  to  help
              them  out  and  provide  them  stable  employment.  So,  what  are  your
              thoughts  on  this  and  how  do  you  think  India  can  address  this  issue?
              Also, what does this overall reveal about Indian society and economy?


              Indian society obviously has lot of layers - class, caste, regional and various other disparities.
              And, as I said earlier, we should be more sensitive to these inequalities and more so during
              the  ongoing  pandemic.  Getting  back,  at  the  global  level,  one  comes  across  the  Great

              Barrington  Declaration  and  the  John  Snow  Memorandum.  These  are  two  broad  schools  of
              thought among medical scientists to address the pandemic.
              The  Declaration  takes  a  position  that  everyone  is  not  equally  vulnerable.  There  are
              demographic differences observed across age and gender and other factors. And hence, with
              reasonable restrictions the relatively less vulnerable people should be allowed to work while
              those  with  greater  vulnerability  (particularly,  those  with  co-morbidities  that  have  greater
              risk factors) are to be kept at a safe distance. This approach is sensitive to migrant labourers

              and their plight. In particular, the approach would suggest that they stay in their destination
              and not return back to their native places.
              As  against  this,  the  Memorandum  has  been  in  favour  of  stricter  restrictions  until  a  safe
              therapeutic  or  medical  intervention  is  available.  While  not  being  explicit  about  livelihood
              concerns,  their  stricter  restrictions  would  also  pre-empt  any  uncalled  for  mobility.  As  an
              aside,  currently,  vaccination  is  being  rushed  through.  Even  if  one  allays  the  scientific

              concerns on account of emergency approval (that is, without going through some checks and
              balances  that  is  done  under  normal  circumstances),  there  can  be  other  major  challenges
              regarding its availability, access, supply chain logistics, public health infrastructure, and the
              reduced focus on other medical conditions. This position has larger economic costs.
              On  mobility,  I  would  also  like  to  refer  to  Nicholas  Christakis  who  is  a  physician  turned
              network sociologist. He wrote a book Apollo’s Arrow where he studied pandemics from 1917-
              18 onwards and provides insights for the current pandemic. He and his colleagues have also

              recently  tracked  the  mobile  phones  that  passed  through  Wuhan  in  January  2020,  before
              lockdown was enforced there, and observed that there is a positive association between the
              distribution  of  these  mobile  phones  across  China  with  the  distribution  of  incidences  of
              infection from Covid in these regions. In short, mobility amplified through network has an
              important  role  in  the  spread  of  the  infection.  Given  this,  restriction  on  mobility  will  be

              helpful. But, this requires other enabling provisions so that people are provided with food,
              shelter, health care, and are also compensated for their livelihood.
              Q6.  You  talked  about  the  decentralised  approach.  Who  do  you  think
              would take the responsibility in rural area or even in a municipality?
              What  would  be  the  policy  suggestion  according  to  you  for  this
              decentralised approach?

              A benefit of doubt could have been given in 2020 but if someone says that they have still not

              developed these things in 2021, one would be surprised. Odisha, which has some strengths in
              disaster management were the first state to declare lockdown in March 2020 when there were
              fewer cases. Further, Government of Odisha, much before the first peak,


                                                                                                                 28]]></page><page Index="32"><![CDATA[during  the  return  of  native  migrants,           Q7.  Some  macroeconomists  in
              provide broad guidelines and authorised              India  are  of  the  view  that
              the sarpanch with the power of a district            spending  on  NREGA  should  be
              magistrate  along  with  some  amount  of
              financial autonomy.                                  increased as it is considered to
                                                                   be  a  business  cycle  stabiliser.
              Today,  in  2021,  after  one  year  of              What  is  your  view  on  NREGA
              experience  we  should  have  been  much             spending  during  the  Covid
              more  prepared.  This  is  so  because  the          period?
              past  pandemics  have  shown  multiple
              spikes.  Even  if  one  were  to  believe  that      Yes,  of  course,  if  people  are  not  able  to
              the current virus in on its wane, there is           get  enough  jobs  at  the  local  level  then
              talk among experts that one could expect             NREGA can be of help. Extension of the
              similar  kind  of  virus  in  the  future.           scheme to urban areas (as suggested by
              Whether it takes the form of a pandemic              Drèze  on  account  of  job  losses  in  the
              or  not  is  a  different  point,  but  localised    pandemic)  will  also  be  welcome.  The
              impact  are  likely  to  be  there.  All  these,     scheme being demand-based has in-built
              call  for  strengthening  the  local  bodies,        checks  and  will  not  be  a  burden  on
              not  just  to  address  an  emergency                exchequer  if  alternative  opportunities
              situation, but with permanent features to            are  available.  However,  note  that
              improve availability and access of public            provisioning  for  NREGA  in  the  budget
              utilities,  and  to  strengthen  the  local          estimates  for  2021-22  when  compared
              economy.  This  will  also  allow  decision-         with the revised estimates of 2020-21 has
              making at the local level with evidence-             decreased  by  -35%.  With  reduction  in
              based  reasoning,  which  means  that                funds,  those  implementing  the  scheme
              research  capacities  that  feed  into  public       will dissuade job creation under NREGA.
              policy  also  need  to  be  strengthened  at         The pandemic is a time when additional
              the local level.
                                                                   budget  could  have  been  allocated  for
                                                                   such schemes.
              On  evidence-based  reasoning,  one  is
              reminded  of  an  opinion  attributed  to            The  activities  under  NREGA  could  be
              John  Maynard  Keynes  who  when                     linked  to  boost  the  local  economy.  For
              confronted that he seems to be changing              instance,  allowing  work  in  one’s  one
              his  position  had  pointed  out  that  if           farms.  Maharashtra  had  done  this  in  its
              evidence  changes  then  he  changes  his            EGS, prior to NREGA. In Palghar, earlier
              position.  We  should  be  pragmatic  and            part      of      undivided       Thane,
              allow  people  to  take  decisions,  and  not        implementation of EGS led to revival of
              admonish them for mistakes when their                rural economy through agricultural and
              intentions  were  honest  and  sincere,  but         horticultural   development.    It   also
              they  should  be  open  to  gathering  of            brought  about  reduction  in  seasonal
              evidence    and   evaluating   these    to           migration,   increased   enrolment     in
              examine  and  revise  their  position  when          schools,  and  increased  consumption  of
              required. It is important that people who            fruits that are nutritionally beneficial. At
              take  advantage  of  this  for  their  rent-         the  same  time,  if  not  implemented
              seeking  activities  are  kept  away  from           properly,  these  could  lead  to  rent
              such positions.
                                                                   seeking.  In  other  words,  NREGA  can  be
                                                                   positively  used  with  necessary  checks
                                                                   and  balances.  If  used  appropriately,  it
                                                                   can have multiplier effects.




                                                                                                                 29]]></page><page Index="33"><![CDATA[ARTICLES FROM




                                       STUDENTS







































                                                A TALE OF TWO IN THE CITY
        A TALE OF TWO IN

        THE CITY
                                                                  SHIBANJAN DUTTA

          -By Shibanjan Dutta

                                               How about someone stuck in a house which isn’t even just a set of
                                               four walls with a roof over it, let alone the attributes which make it
                                               a  home?  How  about  waking  up  every  day  to  a  reality  with
                                               horripilation and threat of existence, same as what had haunted you
        AN                                     in your dreams a few hours ago? Sounds sensationalised right? Yes,
        ETHNOGRAPHIC                           it would have seemed the same to me, a snippet out of a Hollywood

        STUDY OF THE                           fiction,  if  the  COVID-19  lockdown  didn’t  turn  this  into  a  reality.
        EFFECTS OF                             While most of us were commenting on the news and plight of the
        PANDEMIC ON                            thousands  with  some  mere  words  on  social  media,  we  were

        DAILY WAGE-                            implicitly  shedding  off  responsibilities  with  false  hopes  on
        EARNERS                                institutions  taking  care  of  them.  This  article  is  based  on  a  set  of
                                               telephonic  surveys  that  were  conducted  on  the  urban  poor  and  I
                                               hope to revisit a glimpse of the reality that haunted many during
            - By Sagar Kumar                   the COVID-19 lockdown.







                                                                                                                  30]]></page><page Index="34"><![CDATA[Rina Singh had earlier been an ayah at a private hospital. She didn’t have the luxury of the
              sophistication of being termed as a nurse. Later in time she wasn’t accepted for re-joining
              after  going  through  the  trauma  of  a  tumour  surgery  which  made  her  memory  somewhat
              impaired.  Her  husband  had  abandoned  her  long  back  leaving  behind  two  daughters  and  a

              son. Both of her daughters had been married off in spite of one being just 20. Her only son
              hardly  cared  for  her,  with  him  having  shifted  away  to  a  different  place.  Rina,  55  normally
              earns her living by taking care of patients, after being privately hired by families on a daily
              basis.  Now  as  lockdown  was  imposed  on  the  city  and  public  transport  made  unavailable,
              neither  was  she  demanded  by  her  employers  nor  was  she  able  to  visit  their  places  which
              happened to be some 10 kilometres away from her home. Being a daily wage worker, no one
              was obligated to pay her. Near about one month into the lockdown she had to cycle 20 odd

              Kilometres to her earlier places of work in hope of some assistance only to return with 400
              rupees. Her savings dipped nil and with little hope of normalcy, time could any moment have
              become  a  measure  of  hunger  for  her.  Adding  to  the  problems  were  the  statuses  of  her
              daughters. The husband of one had been fleeing for over one month now in the fear of being
              quarantined, since he migrated back to the city after the lockdown had been imposed. The

              other  daughter  Priyanka  compulsively  added  to  Rina’s  financial  burden.  I  happened  to
              survey Rina and one of her daughters and the state of affairs that unfolded was nothing but
              disturbing.
              When Rina Singh approached the so called authorities for free ration, she was plainly denied

              on the pretext that her son was associated with a political party which differed from theirs.
              Rina in frustration came back home only to throw away the flags and emblems of the party
              which  belonged  to  her  son  in  a  nearby  field.  “Do  I  look  like  a  beggar  at  their  mercy?”
              exclaimed Rina at despair. Both of us knew that situations would force her to give up her cry
              on social justice and eventually frame herself as a beggar adding one more justification to the

              tags  bestowed  upon  us  by  the  developed  nations.  From  the  land  which  advocated  social
              justice  in  its  capability  approach,  this  is  nothing  but  a  very  tragic  irony.  Her  daughter
              illuminated another side of the story. Priyanka was a part of a joint family in one of the slums
              some 4 kilometres away from her mother’s house. She had recently been on conflicting terms
              with her in-laws which made matters more severe for her during the period.


              Her husband was thrown out of his job and he gave into his habit of alcohol a bit more. It was

              a well known secret for them now that alcohol could be bought at a higher price from the
              very personnel’s who had been in charge of prohibiting the sales during lockdown. To make
              matters worse she even got denied of the local distribution facilities which happened to exist
              in  her  locality  with  the  people  there  citing  the  fact  that  others  in  her  family  had  already
              opted for it. Unfortunately none was shared by her family with her. Her one year old child’s
              medical  expenses  and  minimal  ration  needs  were  thus  taken  care  of,  by  her  already

              distressed mother Rina.



                                                                                                                 31]]></page><page Index="35"><![CDATA[The  narratives  of  Rina  and  Priyanka  challenged      But  it’s  worth  mentioning  that  the  provision  for
       every bit of the social and economic fabric. No one      free ration, despite being faulty in implementation
       with a brain tumour would cycle 20 Kilometres for        had helped a lot of people.
       some money. The distribution systems were ought

       to  be  instruments  for  assistance  and  not  mercy.   After  witnessing  such  sequence  of  events,  asking
       The  whole  institution  of  joint  family  collapsed  in  them  about  their  update  on  social  distancing
       the  case  of  Priyanka.  The  pandemic  which           seemed  like  a  question  from  a  distant  future.
       withdrew  the  basic  self-reliance  opportunities       When  a  whole  slum  relies  on  two  public  taps  for
       from  people  had  no  silver  lining  for  people  like  drinking   and    non-drinking    needs,    when

       them.  In  the  city  where  the  two  are  mere         community  toilets  are  overburdened,  how  can
       representatives,  the  duality  of  population  as  a    they ensure social distancing even if they wished?
       whole had never been such worse.                         Sometimes the issue of job loss seemed to have hit
                                                                them  so  had  that  the  answers  of  every  question
       Most  of  the  housemaids  I  interviewed  had           turned  out  to  be  a  request  for  a  job.  While  some
       emerged  to  be  the  sole  bread  earners  for  their   expected  financial  assistance  after  the  survey,
       family thus altering the ‘stereotypical pre-historic’    some  repented  about  their  unawareness  after

       gender roles. Most of their sons and husbands had        learning  just  the  names  of  so  many  government
       been  thrown  out  of  employment  now.  Sushoma         schemes that existed.
       Achariya, a housemaid, mentioned in despair how
       her son who earlier used to be a transporter is now      With  a  second  wave  of  the  pandemic  at  the  brim
       trying his luck on selling vegetables only to watch      and speculations of a second lockdown rising, we
       most  of  them  perish.  The  influx  of  many  such     can’t afford to forget the misery that was inflicted

       vegetable  sellers  had  managed  to  keep  the  prices  on  a  major  proportion  of  people.  While  many
       at  competitive  levels  but  businesses  such  as       obligations  towards  them  could  be  dodged  by  a
       grocery  shops,  medicine  shops  had  started           simple  notion  of  ‘Act  of  God’  and  suddenness  of
       charging  a  premium.  This  higher  price  of  living,  things  in  the  first  time,  if  there  happens  to  be  a
       along with steeply falling incomes had taken a toll      second  lockdown,  and  such  experiences  re-
       on their real income more than ever. To mitigate         emerge, we would be held much more responsible
       this when they turned their faces towards the local      for being unable to cushion off their miseries yet

       ration  shops,  excuses  start  emerging.  Digitised     again!
       ration  cards  had  suddenly  gained  utmost
       importance and people without them were plainly
       denied rations. Unavailability of goods at the fair      Shibanjan  Dutta  is  a  student  of  M.Sc.  2020-22
       price  shops  was  also  an  issue.  The  situation      batch.
       emerged to be such that half of the ration from the

       shops were procured by the local party offices to
       rebrand  them  under  a  political  colour  and  some
       were  being  procured  by  local  businesses  at  a
       slightly  higher  price.  The  existence  of  such
       leakages    challenged  the  food  distribution
       schemes. Furthermore most people were unaware
       of  other  government  schemes  that  existed  thus

       revealing  the need for awareness programs among
       them.



                                                                                                                 32]]></page><page Index="36"><![CDATA[AN ETHNOGRAPHIC STUDY OF THE

              EFFECTS OF PANDEMIC ON DAILY WAGE-

                                                  EARNERS


                                                  SAGAR KUMAR
































      In this article, I will try to analyze the radical transformation in the daily lives of common people of our
      country due to the coronavirus pandemic with the help of the experiences of people working in the informal

      sector like hawkers, vegetable vendors, pakoda-sellers, etc. by using ethnographic research methods. Also, I
      will try to explain how these people have themselves evaluated this change and have been surviving despite
      it.
                                                                                   OTHER NEWS
                                                                                   AND
      In the first quarter of the twenty-first century, all the socio-economic aspects of common life were going
      through  severe  turns  of  ups  and  downs.  In  the  first  decade  of  the  new  millennium,  we  saw  how  the
                                                                                   DEVELOPMENTS:
      economies of nations like India and China reached high growth rates and started contributing to the world
      economy majorly. However, the first decade ended with one of the most significant crises of modern times -
                                                                                   T o u r i s m   G e t s   a   B o o s t
      the 2008 Financial Crisis – which originated in the U.S. but impacted most of the leading economies. Now,
                                                                                   i n   J u l y   -   3
      unfortunately, the second decade of the millennium is coming to an end with a pandemic that has already
      affected us badly enough to completely change the course of our daily lives. I hope by the end of the first
      quarter of this century, we overcome this disease and regain a sense of normalcy in our lives.



      As we all know, in the first quarter of the 20th century, the Spanish flu led to many deaths and changed
      social life radically. Along with the flu, came calamities like famines and many other diseases which spread
      very rapidly and altered the daily life of people across the globe as well as across India. A similar event is
      taking place in the 21st century as well when people are suffering from the coronavirus pandemic across the
      world, and they are having to adapt to radical changes in their daily life. Almost everybody on the planet is
      affected by this pandemic directly or indirectly. No matter who they are, what are they doing – some way or

      the other, their daily lives were changed to an unimaginable extent.




                                                                                                                 33]]></page><page Index="37"><![CDATA[This analysis is based on the study I conducted in       Initially,  they  thought  that  the  lockdown  will  be
       my  residential  area  where  around  10-12  street      only for a day but the day after Sunday, when P.M.
       vendors  gather  daily  and  sell  different  items  like  announced that the lockdown will continue for a
       pakoda,  samosa,  pani-puri,  dosa,  pan,  vegetables,   week  and  then  further  extended  it  for  21  days,
       etc.,  and  thereby,  earn  a  respectable  income.  I   they  were  at  a  loss  about  how  to  maintain  their
       personally know almost everyone because most of          daily  lifestyle.  As  they  have  no  other  source  of
       them  sell  their  items  just  behind  my  shop  and    income and are fully dependent on what they sell
       many  of  them  buy  their  raw  materials  from  my     on  a  daily  basis,  the  thought  itself  of  surviving  a
       shop.  So,  it’s  convenient  for  me  to  interact  with  complete lockdown was very difficult for them to
       them for the purpose of this ethnographic study as       fathom.
       I have watched them selling these items from my
       early  childhood.  The  only  change  that  I  had
       noticed  in  all  this  while  is  the  hierarchical    At  the  onset  of  the  lockdown,  they  didn’t  quite
       transition in ownership which has been gradually        understand its basic motive and were overall a bit
       taking place from generation to generation.             critical  of  the  government’s  moves.  In  the  early
                                                               days of the lockdown, listening to various rumors
       When  I  started  to  talk  to  them  regarding  this   doing the rounds, they thought that the virus only
       study, initially they seemed to feel very awkward       infected  people  who  came  from  China  and  other
       and  hesitant  as  nobody  like  me  had  approached    foreign countries. However, after a few days, when
       and tried to initiate such a conversation with them     they started to get the actual idea about the virus,
       before. At first, they outright asked me why I am       how  it  spreads  rapidly  and  affects  our  health
       doing  this  and  don’t  I  have  to  study  big  bulky  system,  they  eventually  started  appreciating  the
       books  since  I  am  currently  enrolled  in  a  higher  actions  of  the  government.  Moreover,  during  the
       degree  course.  They  wanted  to  know  then  where    first phase of the lockdown, they were allowed to
       lies the significance of this study in the context of   sell  their  food  items  till  7  p.m.  according  to  the
       the curriculum of my course. According to them,         state government guidelines since at that time the
       students  should  only  study  to  get  “jobs”,         cases  in  Jharkhand  were  quite  low.  But  later  on,
       otherwise  join  the  family  business  or  parental    when  cases  started  to  rise  in  our  district
       profession.  They  don’t  have  any  idea  about  this  (Dhanbad),  then  our  District  Collector  announced
       kind  of  analysis  which  is  understandable  given    complete  lockdown,  and  only  ration  shops  and
       nobody  in  their  family  has  even  completed  the    vegetable  shops  were  allowed  to  open  along  with
       higher secondary. n their families, usually, people     the . . .
       study  till  class  6-7  and  very  few  of  them  go  for
       matriculation in the local government school. So, I
       started the conversation by trying to explain what
       this  is  all  about  –  the  topic  and  purpose  of  my
       analysis and thereby, earn some confidence from
       them  after  which,  in  3-4  days,  the  conversation
       between us became quite fluid. Since I knew them
       very  well,  I  didn’t  have  to  face  any  kind  of
       difficulty  in  getting  from  them  the  specific
       information I required for this study.  First of all,
       like  us,  they  were  all  very  shocked  and  in  panic
       when  they  came  to  know  about  the  complete
       lockdown  after  listening  to  the  Prime  minister’s
       speech on 23rd March, 2020












                                                                                                                 34]]></page><page Index="38"><![CDATA[medical  clinics  and  shops,  although  just  for  the   had to face the problem of credit then as, before
      limited period of 6 hours. This selective allowance      the  lockdown,  sellers  in  the  mandi  gave  them  a
      for  shops  to  function  actually  made  these  small   time  window  to  sell  their  products  and  pay  the
      vendors, in a sense, a bit jealous and they started      price  within  10  days.  They  couldn’t  avail  this
      complaining     about   the   guidelines   of   the      mechanism  of  deferred  payments  now  and  had
      government.  Meanwhile,  many  of  them  started         there are a few policies that are still quite helpful
      making a shift towards other kinds of professions        to  them  for  their  survival  but  the  point  to  note
      like selling coal, etc. When the shops were finally      here is that they, in no way, should be construed as
      announced to open, the prices of every necessary         any favor to them by the government. Lastly, it has
      good  and  those  of  staple  foods  started  to  rise   been easily noticeable to me that, like most of us,
      steeply  due  to  high  demand  and  it  became  very    they are also very optimistic people and live with
      difficult  for  the  local  shops  to  completely  meet  the  hope  that  the  vaccine  will  arrive  as  early  as
      this high demand. Many of them were selling their        possible and reach everyone across the society as
      items from their home itself, but the sale was half      they  have  seen  with  other  vaccines  like  Polio
      or  less  than  half  of  what  they  used  to  sell  in  the  vaccine  in  the  past.  In  this  article,  I  have  tried  to
      normal  times.  When  others  came  to  know  about      give  a  comprehensive  overview  of  how  the
      this  selling-from-  home  option,  they  also  started  pandemic  has  radically  transformed  the  lives  of
      to  think  differently  and  went  on  to  sell  their   the  common  people  around  us  who  work  in  the
      products by going to different localities on cycles      informal  sector  and  are  worst  hurt  by  the
      or motorcycles. Many of the sellers started to use       pandemic. This article still leaves out certain issues
      sanitizer  very  frequently  and  wore  gloves           which  were  personal  to  the  people  studied  and
      although they had never heard of sanitizer before.       hence, they didn’t want to discuss with me but are
      Some  of  them  even  started  accepting  online         still  important  in  addressing  the  concerns  the
      payments  through  Google  Pay,  PhonePe,  etc.  So,     pandemic  has  raised  about  the  situation  of  the
      one positive thing that came out of this lockdown        daily wage-earners of our nation. I hope any policy
      was their getting to know about how to use these         that is framed in the future to mitigate the adverse
      payment  methods  which  helped  make  their             effects  of  the  pandemic  takes  into  account  the
      business  digital  to  some  extent.  However,  selling  struggle  of  these  people  and  hence,  provides  the
      on bikes and cycles increased their input costs by       economy  with  a  more  balanced  version  of
      quite  an  amount,  and  hence,  their  profit  margin   development.
      decreased.  Since,  they  already  earn  a  very
      moderate amount of income (about ₹200-250/day,           Sagar Kumar is a student of M.Sc. 2020-22 batch.
      on an average), this further lowered it to ₹150 or
      less owing to lesser sales and higher input costs.




      The  case  with  vegetable  hawkers  was  different
      because  before  the  lockdown  they  had  to  travel
      around 5 km to get the vegetables from the mandi,
      but  as  the  mandi  is  a  highly  crowded  space,  the
      police  had  to  strictly  stop  all  activity  over  there.
      So, now they had to travel far away from the local
      wholesale  market  -  around  25  km  per  day  to
      procure  the  vegetables  for  selling.  They  had  to
      leave  their  homes  daily  around  4  a.m.  as  the
      market stayed open only from 4-6 a.m. They also










                                                                                                                 35]]></page><page Index="39"><![CDATA[COVID-19: IMPACT AND


                              LESSONS LEARNT






                                              JAI MOHAN PANDIT




































       The  COVID-19  started  in  India  in  the  beginning  of  2020.  The  subsequent  lockdown  announced  by  the
       Government of India on March 24 impacted the education sector like any other sector for which no one,
       more  so  the  education  sector,  was  unprepared.  The  entire  organisational  functioning  of  the  Higher
       Education  Institutions  (HEIs),  such  as;  student  admission,teaching/research,conducting  examinations,
       academic administration, campus maintenance, student learning support systems including the library and
       IT facilities, campus safety, and security measures, were re-engineered with a paradigm shift.



       IGIDR was prompt to take immediate action and decided to send the student’s home. For several HEIs, it
       was  the  Holi  /  spring  break,  and  few  students  were  already  on  vacation.  The  promptness  and  the  HEIs
       proactive actions saved several lives and resulted in overcoming a lot of hassles. IGIDR allowed some of the
       students to stay back, realising their practical problems. We ensured necessary hostel stay arrangements,
       including the food, safety, and hygiene issues. By the time lockdown was announced, the majority of the

       students had returned home safely.


       Despite  the  numerous  challenges,  most  HEIs,  particularly  the  national  HEIs  located  in  the  metros  and
       cities, quickly geared up to meet the pedagogy challenges, experimented with novel methods, and achieved
       adorable  success  in  the  process.  IGIDR  had  dealt  with  it  by  being  very  agile,  and  agility  was  vital  even
       before the government announced the lockdown.Some of the HEIs initially had to face many challenges,
       which resulted in delays and even cancellations of several academic programs, including exams/admission

       tests, etc.





                                                                                                                36]]></page><page Index="40"><![CDATA[The other important issue was about being able to        IGIDR  being  a  residential  campus,  had  an
       function normally. There were two dimensions: i)         additional  responsibility  to  take  care  of  the
       the  Institution's  smooth  functioning  and  ii)        campus community. Institute appointed a COVID-

       continued  teaching  &  research  work.  It  is  highly  19  task  action  force  committee  chaired  by  our
       laudable  that  both  academic  and  non-academic        Director. The committee had a very tough task to
       employees  played  a  crucial  role  in  ensuring  the   ensure  the  safety,  security  protocols  etc.,  of  he
       smooth  functioning  of  the  Institute.  We  already    campus  community.  The  UGC  and  other
       had  some  digital  and  online  systems  in  place.     regulatory bodies too played a very proactive role
       However, the COVID-19 has pushed us to use these         in  providing  the  relevant  guidelines  to  the  HEIs

       systems proactively.                                     from time to time.


       The  moment  students  reached  home,  the  focus        The  management  of  the  IGIDR,  faculty,  non-
       shifted  from  planning  to  explore  online  teaching   academic staff, and other support teams, played a
       and giving remote access to the library resources        very  pro-active  role  in  ensuring  the  smooth
       and  other  study  materials.  Few  HEIs  had  to  face  functioning  of  the  Institute.  Every  employee  got
       challenges   for   enabling    online   education.       involved in the mission of smooth functioning of

       Challenges  also  involved  encouraging  employees       the Institute. All these events involved meticulous
       and  students  to  get  conversant  with  the  online    planning,    swift    action    from    the    top
       systems  such  as  computer  systems  at  home,  the     management/authorities,      hard     work     and
       software required to get connectivity, etc.              dedication  from  both  the  academic  and  non-
                                                                academic sides. Our staff members, including the

       We  started  deliberations  on  dealing  with  those     Administration,    Accounts,    Estate,   Library,
       students not having access to the internet facility      Students  Office,  and  particularly  the  IT  team
       in some remote places. IGIDR tried to support such       members,  had  to  work  very  hard  to  ensure
       students with additional facilities. Accordingly, the    seamless  support.  In  normal  conditions,  the
       concerns  of  the  students  were  addressed  in  the    employees  of  the  HEIs  are  expected  to  work  for
       best  possible  way  in  a  short  time.  We  provided   eight  hours  a  day.  However,  there  were  no  such
       needy  students  with  laptops/digital  gadgets  on  a   limits  during  the  pandemic  crisis,  and  the

       loan  basis.  We  supported  our  faculty  members  to   employees  had  to  stretch  beyond  regular  duty
       upgrade  their  teaching  aids.  We  also  temporarily   hours, including the weekends and the holidays.
       provided our staff with laptops/desktops, enabling
       them  to  work  from  home  and  even  reimbursing
       their cost towards internet connectivity.








       We  initiated  various  academic  events  and  large  conferences  during  2020-21.  In  normal  circumstances
       organising an event involves a lot of effort. Even though it has several benefits, the physical organisation of
       an event has particular challenges of ensuring adequate attendance and substantial financial commitments,
               "There's nothing quite like feasting on delicious food and drinking
       etc. However, during the COVID-19 time, we could organise academic events very efficiently in the online
       mode.  The  online  way  also  improved  the  quality  of  attendance  drastically.  People  participated  not  only
                                 good wine with your family and friends." organised  the  academic
       from  India  but  from  different  parts  of  the  world  too.  Likewise,  several  HEIs
       programs online during the pandemic times. The attendance of the quality people also gave a significant
       boost to the brand building of the HEIs.





                                                                                                                 37]]></page><page Index="41"><![CDATA[As we advance, most likely, the hybrid model would stay for some more time in

            higher  education  institutions.  One  can  do  things  online,  so  certain  things
            probably  will  continue  in  physical  space.  However,  online  programs  can't  ever
            replace  physical  campuses.  Students  learn  from  teachers,  learn  from  their
            batchmates and seniors through actual interaction. They also learn from students
            from other subjects by being present in the library, cafeteria, etc. So, while virtual
            teaching may extend the reach of only one source of learning, it compromises on
            the  advantages  of  physical  campus.  Other  extracurricular  activities  are  equally

            important  for  the  overall  development  of  students;  they  are  also  getting
            compromised. We should look at an interim arrangement to mitigate the damage
            caused by COVID-19 rather than as an ideal system.


            On  the  other  hand,  risks  are  involved  for  those  HEIs  who  won't  go  with  the
            flow.COVID-19  has  taught  us  the  importance  of  digital/online  systems,  flexible

            governance  and  automation.  To  maintain  quality  and  efficiency,  a  significant
            investment is required to facilitate the digitisation systems in the HEIs.










                                                                     Jai Mohan Pandit is the Registrar at IGIDR.






                                                                                                                 38]]></page><page Index="42"><![CDATA[LIBRARY




       SERVICES DURING




       COVID-19






                                       LIBRARY TEAM





       Since  the  pandemic  struck  in  March  2020,

       IGIDR  Library  is  making  all  the  efforts  to
       meet  the  information  needs  of  faculty
       members,  students,  and  staff  albeit  remotely
       and  to  some  extent  physically  to  the  on-
       campus  users.  The  overall  experience  was
       different  even  though,  we  had  some  digital
       services from pre-Covid times.



       Immediately,  after  the  physical  library  was
       closed, we started off with our email support
       services,  sending  the  required  papers  and
       data    requests      from     the    subscribed      e-
       resources  and  links  for  free  e-books  made

       available  by  publishers.  Soon,  we  realized
       this  may  not  be  adequate  to  meet  the  users'
       demands  24x7.  Hence,  we  embarked  on
       providing  off-campus  access  to  subscribed  e-
       resources.  With  the  kind  help  of  INFLIBNET
       and  the  IT  team  of  IGIDR,  we  were  able  to
       setup    ‘Shibboleth’      off-campus      access     to

       subscribed e-journals and e-databases.


       This  move  augmented  and  helped  in  better  access  and  utilization  of  e-resources  by  the  faculty
       members and students. In addition, the institute’s VPN access was also made available to access some
       of  the  e-resources,  which  were  not  accessible  through  ‘Shibboleth’.  Moreover,  we  are  regularly

       answering  users’  queries  received  through  emails  and  issuing  printed  books  to  on  campus  faculty
       members and students and, also to others staying in Mumbai as and when requested.


                                                                                                                 39]]></page><page Index="43"><![CDATA[During the pandemic and the period of lockdown,         procuring  the  available  ones  and  provided  access
       the  second  big  challenge  was  upkeeping  of  the    remotely.  Now,  we  have  also  begun on  migrating
       physical  library  and  its  resources  from  dust,     library servers to new ones to make these systems
       insects, and humidity. We took off this journey and     robust for future use. We were able to do all this
       with  the  help  of  Estate  department  could  get  the  with the support of authorities library committee
       library  cleaned  and  pest  controlled  on  a  periodic  members  and  staff  of  all  the  departments  and

       basis  initially  and  from  August  2020  on  a  regular  support teams.
       basis, so that the library can be put for immediate
       use  as  soon  the  institute  reopens.  During  these  In  the  post-Covid  era,  we  perceive,  libraries  are
       challenging times with the limited on campus staff      going to be resilient and regain their momentum.
       support,  we  continued  to  acquire  new  resources,   However,  as  it  happened  after  the  emergence  of
       conducted library committee meetings and events,        the Internet, there will be some amount of shift in

       renewed  subscriptions  to  both  print  and  online    users’  behavior  regarding  the  use  of  the  physical
       journals,  handling  of  day-today  administration,     library and its resources, but they will continue to
       contributing metadata of IGIDR working papers to        use print resources for reasons of non-availability
       RePEc,    bringing    out   monthly     ‘ÉconBuzz’      in e-formats and secondly, the libraries will not be
       newsletter  on  a  regular  basis  and  sharing  useful  able to procure the e-versions owing to enormous
       information  through  email  and  library  Twitter      cost,  which  is  usually  ten  times  higher  than  the
       handle  ‘@igidrlib’.  Among  the  new  resources,       printed books. In addition, the licensing issues and

       procurement  of  course  specific  e-books,  was        subscription  mode  of  procurement  will  also
       challenging as many of these were not available in      prevent this from happening especially in the case
       e-formats, however, we put in our efforts in            of e-books.




























       We believe, in the future, IGIDR library users would
       adore  the  physical  library,  as  much  as  they  like  to
       read  resources  from  their  personal  devices  and
       comforts of their homes/hostel rooms. We will thrive
       hard  and  change  ourselves  to  changing  times  as
       change is always constant, which will help us see the

       things as seen by our users. Also, try our best to save
       our users from ‘infodemic’.






                                                                                                                 40]]></page><page Index="44"><![CDATA[CAMPUS RECRUITMENT

       IN A PANDEMIC


       STRUCK ECONOMY



                                                    Lukshya Verma















        The legacy built by the alumni and faculty at IGIDR, along with the determination of students facilitated a
           successful campus recruitment season amidst an economic slowdown that preceded the pandemic.


       During the summer of 2020, as the institute's administration worked hard to build digital infrastructure
       and an academic calendar that would ensure students’ academics continued unhampered, the placement
       committee at IGIDR faced a different challenge of coordinating with companies that had offered summer
       internships.  The  revised  academic  calendar  had  overlapped  with  the  summer  internship  duration  and  it

       seemed impossible to manage both. However, with the help of concessions from companies and the grit
       showed  by  students,  the  summer  internship  program  was  a  success  in  terms  of  the  record  number  of
       corporate internships and pre-placement offers. But the situation was about to get much more challenging
       for the placement committee when it became clear that the pandemic was here to stay and would have a
       severe impact on the final recruitment that was supposed to be held later that year.

                                                                     Challenges of a New Normal



                                                                     The challenge being faced by the committee
                                                                     was two-fold. The first was that the economic
                                                                     slowdown caused many firms to cut back on
                                                                     recruitment  numbers  and  some  even  froze
                                                                     hiring. This was going to have a direct effect

                                                                     on  the  institute’s  placement  statistics.  The
                                                                     other  challenge  was  that  the  pandemic  had
                                                                     made the existing on-day placement process
                                                                     obsolete.  It  had  to  be  replaced  by  a
                                                                     completely new process that was to be built
                                                                     from  scratch  and  had  never  been  tried
                                                                     before. The rolling placement process, which
                                                                     is  generally  followed  by  most  other

                                                                     institutes, is not feasible for IGIDR due to the
                                                                     small batch size and the strictly enforced rule



                                                                                                                 41]]></page><page Index="45"><![CDATA[with  the  entire  batch  as  well  as  faculty  advisors
                                                                and  members  of  the  administration  was  also
                                                                important  to  establish  clear  communication
                                                                between  the  various  stakeholders  so  that  all  the

                                                                processes could be conducted smoothly.
                                                               Seeking Alumni Support


                                                               The  biggest  challenge  before  any  placement

                                                               committee  is  to  get  new  recruiters  and  to
                                                               encourage  existing  ones  to  offer  better  and  more
                                                               diverse  profiles.  This  becomes  even  more
                                                               challenging  in  a  recessionary  phase  when
                                                               recruiters become highly averse towards exploring
       against  rejection  and  multiple  offers.  Therefore,  new  institutes.  Organisations  that  have  been
       IGIDR  has  been  following  a  placement  week         regular recruiters at our institute are always keen
       system  that  is  much  more  fast-paced  and  gets     to  continue  hiring.  This  is  because  the  alumni  of
       completed within a day or two. It was important to      our  institute  have  built  a  good  reputation  among
       preserve  the  essence  of  the  placement  week        their colleagues and seniors, and are a testament to
       process  so  as  to  benefit  from  it  while  keeping  in  the  quality  of  education  and  training  provided  at

       mind the limitations of the virtual setup.              IGIDR.  However,  due  to  small  batch  sizes  and
       The  employment  market  across  the  country
                                                               limited promotion of the institute across the years,
       witnessed  a  sharp  widening  of  inequality  during
                                                               such  organisations  are  few.  Therefore,  it  becomes
       the  pandemic.  While  on  one  end,  thousands  of     important to seek the help of our alumni, many of
       people  were  losing  jobs  and  unemployment
                                                               who  are  in  strategic  positions  across  various
       reached  record  high  levels,  on  the  other  end  the
                                                               companies.
       most prestigious and well-known institutes across
                                                               This  year,  along  with  directly  reaching  out  to  the
       the  country  saw  an  improvement  in    their         alumni  for  their  help,  we  made  conscious  efforts
       placement statistics. In order to be situated at the
                                                               throughout  the  year  to  take  measures  that
       fortunate  end,  the  students  needed  to  be  well
                                                               strengthen the bond between the alumni and their
       equipped  with  the  knowledge  of  their  course
                                                               alma  mater.  Starting  from  an  informal  closing
       material along with other skills that are considered
                                                               report that compiled various messages sent by our
       desirable  in  the  industry.  To  facilitate  sharing  of
                                                               alumni  containing  their  memories  of  IGIDR  and
       such  knowledge,  the  placement  committee  came
                                                               the role that it played in shaping their careers, to
       up  with  multiple  new  initiatives  such  as  the
                                                               keeping  the  LinkedIn  page  active  with  regular
       internship  discussion  program,  sessions  with
                                                               posts regarding the activities and achievements at
       immediate seniors, etc. Having  regular meetings
                                                               IGIDR, there was a sincere effort done to rekindle




                                                                                                                 42]]></page><page Index="46"><![CDATA[the sense of belongingness that alumni have with their alma mater. The members of the Alumni Committee
       also played an integral role in this by organising virtual sessions with alumni from diverse disciplines and
       backgrounds.
       The alumni of any institute are its most valuable assets, and having a robust network that facilitates both

       inter and intra batch communication is essential in strengthening the reputation of an institute. There is
       much that needs to be further done in this regard, and we are hopeful that the future batches will do a great
       job in expanding the ambit of such initiatives.
       D-Day



       The Placement Season for 2021 was scheduled in the third week of December, and by the first week of the
       month, we had received confirmation from a good number of companies. It was in contrast to the situation
       just a month ago, when there were hardly any confirmations and it appeared that it would be the worst
       placement season in the history of IGIDR. But getting confirmations accounted for only half the work. The
       new virtual process that we had built needed to work perfectly. Any disruption or breakdown in the system
       would not only add to the anxiety of students appearing for placements but also tarnish our reputation in
       front  of  the  companies.  Therefore,  all  the  members  of  the  Placement  Committee  spent  hours  with  their

       designated  company  officials  before  the  placement  day,  explaining  to  them  the  rules  and  the  process  to
       avoid any confusion on the final day. Multiple simulations were conducted with the batch to ensure the
       process worked seamlessly and that everyone was familiar with it.
       The placements went on for a week, and every slot witnessed a higher number of offers than what we had
       initially anticipated. This showed that the students were well prepared and had worked extremely hard.
       The company officials congratulated the committee on conducting a well-laid-out process and some even

       inquired to know more about it, as they wanted to replicate the process for recruitments at other institutes.
       Despite the unprecedented scenario, we were able to conduct one of the most successful placement seasons
       ever conducted at IGIDR.
       The Way Forward




       The rapid growth in the field of data analytics and artificial intelligence has created many opportunities for
       students having a robust conceptual understanding of statistics and econometrics. This is also evident from
       the fact that many prestigious institutes across the country are now offering dedicated courses and degrees
       in Data Analytics. The students of IGIDR, an institute known for its specialisation in econometrics courses,

       stand to gain a lot from this digital revolution.
       While IGIDR enjoys a good reputation among various industry leaders and recruiters, there is much that
       needs to be done to realise our full potential. One of the biggest advantages of having a small batch size is
       that every individual with an idea can make themselves heard and ensure their ideas are put into action.
       A good placement record has a positive spillover on attracting talented students from across the country.
       This will not only ensure a more diverse set of students but also help us achieve our vision of developing as

       an institute of high international standing and join the league of world-class centres of excellence.



       Lukshya Verma is a student of M.Sc. 2019-21 batch and a member of Placement Committee, IGIDR.







                                                                                                                 43]]></page><page Index="47"><![CDATA[ALUMNI DISCOURSES IN A


                                           PANDEMIC





                                           ALUM NI CO M M ITTEE

























       IGIDR  Alumni  Association’s  Alumni  Discourses  is  one  of  the  best  initiatives  started  by  our  super-senior
       batch. We hope it'll continue to increase our span of knowledge, thanks to the overwhelming participation
       of our alumni.
       I can proudly quote, "If you have a garden and a library and the support of your alumni, then regardless of
       an academic or a corporate career, you have everything needed to succeed!" Our alumni have distinguished
       themselves in various fields and established their careers in different parts of the world.
       This  year,  we  successfully  conducted  three  episodes  of  Alumni  Discourses  with  an  aim  to  connect  with

       people  from  different  backgrounds.  In  the  first  episode,  we  had  Ms.  Sohini  Choudhuri  (Assistant  Vice
       President at Credit Suisse) and Ms. Ritu Ghosh (Associate Director at UBS) from the M.Sc. 2016 batch, who
       are working extensively in the corporate sector. The two guests gave us an idea of how the corporate world
       works, the kind of challenges that one may face, and how to deal with those challenges. However, what was
       perhaps the most important lesson that we learnt from the two of them was that we need to know our
       value and take a stand for ourselves.

       In  the  second  episode,  we  had  Dr.  Piyush  Tiwari  (Professor  of  Property  at  University  of  Melbourne,
       Australia)  from  the  Ph.D.  1998  batch.  While  cognitive  learning  is  encouraged  at  IGIDR  by  its  renowned
       faculties, Dr. Tiwari made us realize the importance of emotive learning through his experiences. Besides,
       his subject matter expertise in the field of Housing Economics allowed us to learn about something new. He
       also gave us insights on what it is like to pursue a Ph.D.
       In the third and final episode, we had Dr. Padma Sharma (Economist at Federal Reserve Bank of Kansas
       City) from the M.Sc. 2006 batch. She gave a small presentation of her work that she had done at the Federal

       Reserve Bank of Kansas City. After the presentation, she gave her thoughts on what it is like to pursue a
       Ph.D. abroad and the challenges that one may face. She also gave us an approach of how to go about it. Her
       positive attitude and willingness to help was a huge boost for us.
       All  in  all,  it  was  an  absolute  pleasure  to  hear  from  such  eminent  personalities.  In  a  world  where  online
       classes have become the new norm, the way our guests got nostalgic when talking about their campus life

       and what they liked the most about it made us realize what we are missing out on. Having interactions with
       such people gives us motivation to aim high and work harder to achieve our goals.

                                                                                                                 44]]></page><page Index="48"><![CDATA[KAAWISH : A BEACON OF HOPE
















      Kaawish  is  a  student-led  initiative  at  whose  heart  lies  the  belief  in  giving  back  to  society.  The  idea  for
      Kaawish was conceived as a token of gratitude for the non-teaching staff at IGIDR, considering all that they
      do for us. During its inception, all of us volunteers held multiple meetings with the parents to understand

      exactly what they wanted out of these sessions. Some of the main concerns voiced at these meetings were
      improvement in English, strengthening basics, and invigorating interest in academics for the kids. We had
      students  from  the  age  of  5  to  16.  All  the  volunteers  constantly  ensured  that  the  sessions  do  not  become
      monotonous for the kids. For instance, instead of just teaching out of a book for the entire class, we would
      dedicate some time to teach them ABACUS and Vedic mathematics to improve their analytical thinking or
      watch informative English clips and would read storybooks to improve their comprehension of the language

      in the other half of the class.



































      We would also teach them common salutations, how to introduce themselves, and soft skills in general. At
      the end of all this, we would have a 30- minute activity session. They would be given a choice to participate
      in origami making, dance classes, sports sessions, or drawing classes.


      Kaawish started with an idea and a few curious minds in the IGIDR common room and it has been more

      than a year now that it has successfully brought at least some amount of happiness in the lives of many -
      both volunteers and kids alike. It is a sphere where you do not just give back to society but



                                                                                                                 45]]></page><page Index="49"><![CDATA[also learn some of the very beautiful aspects of life. Here, it is not just about teaching a kid allotted to you
       but having the responsibility that the kids take away some valuable lessons from that 1-1.5 hour class. We
       remember  celebrating  International  Women's  Day  together  where  the  students  took  part  in  various
       activities to commemorate the immense contribution of women in our society. We, at KAAWISH, do not
       consider gender equality or the journey towards it as a single-day formality. At each step, we tried to ensure
       that the gender stereotype was broken and along with the kids, we all walk towards gender equality and a
       better tomorrow. As we celebrated Women’s Day, we were again reminded of our duties as students and

       also as fellow citizens.
                                                                However,  fortune  had  some  other  plans.  Only
                                                                when we thought things were in place, we had to
                                                                stop Kaawish classes as Covid guidelines came into
                                                                force.  All  the  volunteers  had  to  return  to  their
                                                                homes. It was a heartbreaking moment for all of us

                                                                and we vowed to resume things once we are back
                                                                at the institute again. As time went on, the scale of
                                                                the pandemic became more and more clear to us,
                                                                and  going  back  was  becoming  more  and  more
                                                                uncertain. So, by September, we decided to wait no

                                                                more  and  planned  to  resume  the  classes  but  this
                                                                time things were different. Instead of the face-to-
                                                                face classes, we had with the kids back in the good
                                                                old  days,  the  mode  of  teaching  and  learning  was
                                                                now online.


       So sadly, we had to do away with the activity sessions but it was very inspiring for us to see the interest
       students had in the classes even without them. The main problem we faced in the online mode was that of
       connectivity  which  hampered  the  smooth  functioning  of  a  class.  It  was  also  very  difficult  to  hold  the
       attention of a kid and make sure that they are understanding whatever we are telling them when we are
       sitting  so  far  away.  However,  we  found  that  things  are  most  important  to  have  during  these  classes  -
       patience and empathy. Patience is important to keep on trying and never give up on the learning outcomes
       and empathy helps oneself to relate with the unfortunate situation that a kid locked down from the world
       of  school,  friends,  and  playground  finds  herself  in.  But  still,  we  are  thankful  for  the  advancement  of

       technology that enables us to interact with them from across the country and talk to each other and learn
       together. From the first day, we have strived to stick to our motive and not let the
       obstacles  overpower  our  determination  of  creating  impact.  Although  the  problems  of  connectivity  and
       arranging a suitable time slot has been a nagging issue in the past few months for all of us - students and
       volunteers alike, yet the continuing enthusiasm of students to attend the classes even in an online mode

       made us relieve from all the troubles the pandemic has brought in. Despite all the hurdles, the students are
       making good progress and we are confident that this initiative will gather more momentum once we can
       shift back to the offline classes hopefully in the near future.


       Kaawish is like a sapling which the IGIDR family planted and nourished together and it grew despite all the
       adversities, giving back more than it takes. It inspires to grow and embodies all the values of IGIDR. We, as
       members of the Kaawish family, hope that it passes on across generations and grows into a big tree under

       whose shade every student of IGIDR gets inspired and learns to grow together.



                                                                                                                 46]]></page><page Index="50"><![CDATA[Campus




        Activitiees













































































                                                                                                                 47]]></page><page Index="51"><![CDATA[IGIDR ACROSS



           GENERATIONS








       From offline






                                      to online

































                                                                                                                 48]]></page><page Index="52"><![CDATA[CROSSWORD











                            1         2
                                                             3
                                                8

                                      9                             4
                                                                                                        F
                                                5        10

                                6                                                                       U

                                            11
                                                       7                                                N






                                         12                                                             C
                                                                                                        O








         Down                                                                                           R

         1. Every business wants to have this but my sister wants to play this. (8)
         2. This cross determines Aggregate Demand.(9)
         3. I literally mean different dispersion.(18)                                                  N
         4. I mean fake.(5)
         5. An economists’ mean way of saying ‘I Love You’:                                             E
         The __________ returns of spending time with you will never diminish.(8)
         6. “All __________ is directed towards producing some effect.” – Alfred
         Marshall. (6)                                                                                  R
         7. When the river meets the sea it forms a _______. (5)




         Across
         1. Keynes said,”_______ can remain irrational longer than you can remain
         solvent.”(6)
         6. Mr. X and Ms. Y are suspected to be in this relationship.(6)
         8. Although you set it, you usually can’t stay within it.(6)
         9. This rate is capable of dirty floating.(8)
         10. When my car kissed my neighbour’s car I heard this.(4)
         11. I always accompany higher returns.(4)
         12. You don’t like it because it erodes the value of money in your pocket.(9)
                                                                                                                49]]></page><page Index="53"><![CDATA[FIND THE WORDS











                                        N E V       E L P O E M T              D





                                        R E S P E N S E F E R




                                        S T R O N S C E E




                                        L I O N E N





                                        T I K K A T






                                    Now arrange the highlighted  boxes,

                      to form the surprise answer as suggested by the below line



                                    I am Contolled by Bulls and Bears.



































                                                                                                                 4850]]></page><page Index="54"><![CDATA[NOSTALGIA









                                    CAMPUS | HOSTEL | MUMBAI


















          "It has been a year since I've left IGIDR and I've come to realize that, what seemed to be daily
       mundane activities during my stay at IGIDR, is what I miss the most now. Running from the hostel
           to make it in time for the 9.30 AM class only to sleep through most of it; sitting outside the
       cafeteria, chatting away with friends, eating my favourite breakfast - medu vada and cold coffee;
        spending the entire evening playing TT, carrom and badminton in the recreation center; staying
               up late on exam nights and meeting up with friends after dinner for a cup of chai.
        Of course there were the special occasions - festival celebrations with everyone on campus, the
        sports and cultural week events which we took quite seriously to be honest, those rare feasts at
        the Director's bungalow, that extra stressful week before placements and birthday celebrations
                                      that lasted till wee hours of the morning.
          All in all, the time that I've spent at IGIDR has been an experience of a lifetime. The place has
        given me memories that I'll always hold close to my heart and friends who have now become an
                                            indispensable part of my life. "
                                                            "                                   - Namrata Sen
                                                                                                 ( M.Sc. 2018-20)





                                                        "IGIDR, a place that beholds countless memories, and
                                                        has given me life-long friends. Wish I could've had the
                                                        opportunity to relive the journey yet again! Right from
                                                          the first semester to the last, every memory will be
                                                            treasured. Be it the sleepless nights before the
                                                        submission of micro assignments, the ceaseless dining
                                                        hall conversations, the night before time series exams,
                                                       the fifth-floor balcony, the cold coffee, the 'anda-maggi ',
                                                       the cats, the leopards, or the red square, will forever be
                                                        etched in my heart. IGIDR and its people will be sorely
                                                        missed. Hope our paths cross soon and get the closure

                                                                              we deserve!"
                                                                                                    - Ipsita Das
                                                                                                    ( M.Sc. 2018-20)




                                                                                                                 51]]></page><page Index="55"><![CDATA["Apart from the library with subscriptions to
         most leading journals, the 24x7 computer
        centre allowing flexible study hours and the
       academic infrastructure in general, the thing
       that struck me the most on the first few days
        was the sports facilities on campus. Ranging
       from carrom and TT to cricket and volleyball,
       there's hardly any sport that isn't played over
        here. What made it even more fun was that
        students, professors, non-teaching staff and
          children would all play side by side. This
       feeling of living in a community and not just a
       hostel is something that separates IGIDR from
             most other academic institutions."

                                      - Sasmit Dutta
                                       ( M.Sc. 2018-20)







                                                                  "The magic of IGIDR is hard to put in a small
                                                                   paragraph. Living in IGIDR campus is like a
                                                                  celebration. Where else can you find yourself
                                                                 being pampered like this. Every person here is
                                                                equal, whether it be a teaching staff, student or

                                                                   non-teaching staff. We all are a part of this
                                                                 small loving family. We eat, play and celebrate
                                                                 every occasion together. I can never forget how
                                                                     even though the pressure of exams and
                                                                  assignments kept us awake at night,  Nagori
                                                                  chai at 4AM just after you clicked the submit
                                                                 button for your assignment was a love. We had
                                                                  one to one interactions with profs due to this
                                                                  small batch size. We used to decide ourselves
                                                                the timing of our exams. Being up and partying
                                                                all night. Going to bed at 4-5am and waking up
                                                                 at 9:30am and rushing to classes with a cup of
                                                                    espresso shot was quite a habit.  Also our

                                                                 Wednesday biryani and Sunday dosas. We all
                                                                 complained about it but we all looked forward
                                                                 to it, Always. IGIDR is not a place. It's a feeling."


                                                                                             - Komal Baranwal
                                                                                                 ( M.Sc. 2018-20)








                                                                                                                 52]]></page><page Index="56"><![CDATA["In my UG course, my batch had students from different backgrounds which was apparent from their
         family income. These differences resulted in a barrier among the students which led to segregation
       and two groups in the batch. To my surprise, there used to be absolutely minimal interaction between
        the two groups. A few of the students tried to be part of the supposedly higher group but did not get
         adequate acceptance. Even my seniors told me that it had been a common phenomenon for years
       especially in Economics and English departments. For students coming from small towns (in my case,
                          coming from a village), it feels like the college is not accepting us.
       I came to IGIDR with the same fear. However, although the students were from different backgrounds
        at IGIDR as well, nothing of that sort happened. I guess hostel accommodation for all and the small
          batch size helped to not have such a segregation. I always felt like at home and the institute had
                           accepted me warmly. My heart keeps a special place for IGIDR. "

                                                                                      - Mritunjay Kumar
                                                                                          ( M.Sc. 2018-20)









                                                                                    "एक खास जगह का आम  दन ...
        “Gar firdaus bar-rue zamin ast, hami asto, hamin asto, hamin
                                      ast.”                                          वो छोटे से सफर म  होती, ल बी
        I am telling you, it would not be an exaggeration to compare                        सी मुलाकात,
         IGIDR campus to heaven. The campus is really very beautiful                  वो बो र ग से ले चर म  चलती,
          and people there enhance its charm even more. This place                        रोचक सी कोई बात,
         brings back so many memories - evening talks, night parties,                वो ठहाक  संग सुरा ती, शाम क
         sports participation, watching movies with friends, festivals                       मसाला चाय,
        celebrations and what not. Life at IGIDR is not only full of thrill            वो  डनर टेबल पर द  जाती,
        and enjoyment but also is a great place to learn and explore.                     फ़ज़ूल सी फ़ज़  राय,

         The small batch size makes the class a family. Faculties are                वो 5th  लोर पर टकराते, वाद
       very approachable, and students can easily interact with them.                       के  नशीले जाम,
       The series of educational seminars throughout the year creates                वो  फर सवेरे जागता सूरज, वो
         a suitable atmosphere for the research orientation and the                    फर मु काती ढलती शाम।"
          scope for the discussion on the current economic aspects.
       Infrastructure and other facilities (badminton court, swimming
          pool, tennis court, library, computer centre, etc.) are very
        amazing. Other than academics, there are many co-curricular
        activities like sports week, cultural week, Ganesh puja, Annual
          day and Saraswati puja which makes this place even more                   - Shubham Singh Lodhi
         lively. Student led initiative "Kaawish" (teaching IGIDR staff's                 ( M.Sc. 2018-20)
           children on weekends ) not only enables we students to
        contribute something towards the society but also makes our

       IGIDR family more united. Certainly, these were one of the best
            years of my life with very amazing people out there. "




                                                                                                                 53]]></page><page Index="57"><![CDATA["IGIDR had wonderful people in it. Seniors who were
                                                        downright competitive about Dumb Charades and

                                                           made me a better player (they also helped in
                                                            numerous other ways, but this is what I will
                                                           remember them for). Canteen staff who were
                                                       always up for friendly banter and sat alongside me
                                                       cheering for India in the World Cup. Professors who

                                                         stayed helpful and patient and saved many lives
                                                            when pesky doubts cropped up just around
                                                       examination season. Guard uncles who smiled and
                                                       waved and once even offered me some home-made
                                                            pickle from their lunches. And friends who I
                                                         inadvertently picked up along the way and now
                                                                 cannot let go of for some reason.

                                                       IGIDR was a wonderful place. Sunsets were magical
                                                            when seen from the fifth-floor balcony. Idli-
                                                        sambhar always tasted better when eaten outside
                                                       the cafeteria. The library was huge and intimidating
                                                           but also cool and exciting and at night, Khan
                                                          Chacha sat at the entrance with his radio and

                                                                 smiled warmly at our tired faces.
                                                          At IGIDR, we raced around campus looking for
                                                       Treasure Hunt clues. We became obsessed with cold
                                                        coffee and nimbu pani, and had long email chains
                                                       discussing the welfare of campus cats. We stayed up
                                                          late for Time Series. We woke up early for Time
                                                                                Series.

                                                       I smile because it happened. I am furious that it was
                                                        torn away from us so soon. And I am excited that
                                                        there are others out there yet to experience life in
                                                         IGIDR, and perhaps one day I can swap campus
                                                                         stories with them."


                                                                                       - Dipanwita Ghatak
                                                                                           ( M.Sc. 2018-20 )













                                                                                                                 54]]></page><page Index="58"><![CDATA[S T U D E N T


                 N E W S L E T T E R


                   C O M M I T T E E
















































                                    IGIDR

                      GEN. A.K.VAIDYA MARG
                          GOREGAON EAST,

                   MUMBAI - 400 065 (INDIA)








                          http://www.igidr.ac.in


                          studentnewsletter@igidr.ac.in


                          IGIDR Newsletter Committee]]></page></pages></Search>